<text id="1">
<raw>
Boy dies
</raw>
</text>
<text id="2">
<raw>
Indonesia has the highest human death toll from bird flu of any nation, and on Wednesday that number grew to 58 when a boy, from Tangerang near Jakarta, died, said the head of the Indonesian health ministry’s bird flu center Runizar Ruesin.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="3">
<raw>
The boy was admitted to hospital in the capital last week and deaths among poultry in his neighbourhood had recently been reported, the WHO said in a statement posted on its Web site.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="4">
<raw>
Muhammad Nadirin, another official at the country’s bird flu center, said hospital staff had to take extra care washing the boy’s corpse because of concerns the virus might infect them.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="5">
<raw>
“He was washed using special protection methods to prevent contagion,” but added he didn’t know if it could be transmitted from human-to-human this way.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="6">
<raw>
The H5N1 virus mostly affects birds, but it has infected 263 people in 10 countries since 2003, killing 157 of them.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="7">
<raw>
Scientists fear the virus could mutate and spread rapidly between people, triggering a pandemic that could sweep the globe in weeks and possibly kill millions.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="8">
<raw>
The outbreak of highly pathogenic H5N1 avian influenza began in Asia in 2003 and spread rapidly in early 2006.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="9">
<raw>
South Korea confirms outbreak of bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="10">
<raw>
SEOUL - South Korea today said a bird flu outbreak at a poultry farm was caused by the highly virulent H5N1 strain of the virus, in the country's first case for three years of the infection that can kill humans.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="11">
<raw>
The Agriculture Ministry said earlier this week it suspected bird flu had killed 6,000 chickens at a farm in the southwest of the country that lies on a path for migratory birds.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="12">
<raw>
"It is the H5N1 strain," a ministry official said by telephone, after test results.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="13">
<raw>
The ministry ordered the culling of 236,000 poultry within a 1,640-foot radius of the farm in North Cholla province about 100 miles from Seoul, a ministry statement said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="14">
<raw>
Quarantine authorities also banned the shipment of more than 5 million poultry from 221 farms within a 6.2-mile radius of the farm.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="15">
<raw>
There were no reports to suggest local residents or quarantine officials had been infected, another Agriculture Ministry official said by telephone.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="16">
<raw>
Between December 2003 and March 2004, about 400,000 poultry at South Korean farms were infected by bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="17">
<raw>
During that outbreak, the country culled 5.3 million birds and spent about $1.6 billion on preventing the disease spreading, officials said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="18">
<raw>
Subsequent testing in the United States indicated at least nine South Korean workers involved in the cull had been infected with the H5N1 virus, but none developed major illnesses.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="19">
<raw>
Since 2003, outbreaks have been confirmed in around 50 countries and territories, according to the World Organization for Animal Health.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="20">
<raw>
North Korea had an outbreak at poultry farms near the capital Pyongyang in February 2005, which led it to cull more than 200,000 chickens and vaccinate 1.1 million poultry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="21">
<raw>
The World Health Organization said that by Nov. 13, there had been 258 cases of human infection of the H5N1 strain since 2003, killing 153 people. Many of the victims were Asians, with 98 deaths in Vietnam and Indonesia, WHO said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="22">
<raw>
Bird flu vaccine shows good results in early trial
</raw>
</text>
<text id="23">
<raw>
CHICAGO - Preliminary results from an early clinical trial of a vaccine for pandemic bird flu suggest the vaccine is safe and well tolerated and may prove effective against divergent strains of the disease, Baxter International Inc said today.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="24">
<raw>
"This is the first clinical demonstration that a candidate H5N1 (bird flu virus) vaccine can induce antibodies that neutralize widely divergent strains of H5N1," said Noel Barrett, vice president of Global research and development for Baxter's vaccines business.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="25">
<raw>
"These preliminary data, which must be confirmed in a larger study, suggest that the vaccine may provide wider protection for a larger number of people before and during a pandemic," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="26">
<raw>
H5N1 mainly affects birds, but experts fear it could mutate into a strain easily transmitted from person to person, capable of killing millions of people in a global pandemic.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="27">
<raw>
An H5N1 virus has killed at least 148 people since 2003, mostly in Indonesia, Vietnam, Thailand and China, according to the World Health Organisation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="28">
<raw>
 Baxter said the clinical trial of the experimental H5N1 pandemic vaccine in 270 healthy adults in Austria and Singapore suggested the vaccine had similar side effects to those reported for seasonal flu vaccines.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="29">
<raw>
The preliminary results suggest the vaccine is highly capable of producing an immune response and can create antibodies to H5N1 even at the lowest dose level, it said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="30">
<raw>
A preliminary analysis of serum samples obtained from study subjects showed the vaccine was able to neutralise the pandemic virus contained in the vaccine as well as other diverse strains of the H5N1 virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="31">
<raw>
Baxter plans to begin a late-stage clinical trial of the vaccine early next year and said it will present final results by the end of 2007.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="32">
<raw>
Deerfield, Illinois-based Baxter has said its cell-based vaccine production system is more rapid than traditional methods using chicken eggs.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="33">
<raw>
Baxter's H5N1 pandemic vaccine candidate was produced using four different antigen concentrations. Two of the concentrations were with and without adjuvant, a substance added to vaccines to improve immune response.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="34">
<raw>
Baxter and a number of other companies are working to develop a vaccine to protect against a potential bird flu pandemic. GlaxoSmithKline Plc in July said its vaccine could be mass produced in 2007.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="35">
<raw>
There is currently no vaccine against the virus, which is now treated with Tamiflu, also known as oseltamivir, an antiviral drug made by Roche and Gilead Sciences Inc.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="36">
<raw>
Glaxo also makes the inhaled drug Relenza under license from Australia's Biota, which also appears to treat both types of flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="37">
<raw>
Schools told to prepare for bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="38">
<raw>
A pandemic will strike New Zealand and schools need to be preparing for it now, the Ministry of Education's pandemic planning manager said today.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="39">
<raw>
Graeme Marshall told the annual meeting of the New Zealand Education Institute there was a high risk of bird flu becoming a pandemic that would strike New Zealand, and it could kill between 30-50,000 people.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="40">
<raw>
"We will get a pandemic at some stage. It's not a question of if, it's a question of when. However, there's no need to panic because an awful lot of us won't die. Something over four million (New Zealanders) won't die."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="41">
<raw>
Not panicking was imperative. People needed to remember the pandemic would pass and life would go on, Mr Marshall said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="42">
<raw>
As government representatives, school staff needed to reflect on how the best of a bad situation could be achieved.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="43">
<raw>
"It is unlikely that communities will thank us if we metaphorically head for the hills," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="44">
<raw>
In preparation for the pandemic schools needed to keep up to date contact lists and teachers should be actively encouraging children to wash their hands properly and blow their noses correctly.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="45">
<raw>
 When a pandemic struck teachers needed to provide as full a service as possible for as long as possible to keep things as near to normal as they could, Mr Marshall said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="46">
<raw>
"I think it will be the sharpest test on our management skills.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="47">
<raw>
"The issue will be monitoring safe and healthy working environments."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="48">
<raw>
Prohibiting students from attending schools was one way medical officers of health might try to stop the spread of infection, he said. Sick students may also be sent home by principals.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="49">
<raw>
Correspondence schooling should be organised for those students, Mr Marshall said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="50">
<raw>
Staff themselves would need to be monitored for signs of sickness, and schools needed to be prepared for up to 50 per cent fewer staff at the height of a pandemic.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="51">
<raw>
"You must be sure to stay home when you're sick. "
</raw>
</text>
<text id="52">
<raw>
Every school should have an action plan in place and individuals should have an emergency kit of medication and food in their own homes, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="53">
<raw>
The Ministry of Health has outlined five stages of a pandemic management strategy. New Zealand is at stage one, the planning stage.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="54">
<raw>
The last major pandemic was the Spanish flu, which hit New Zealand in 1918 and killed 8600 people.Traveller is unlikely to have bird flu, say Australia officials
</raw>
</text>
<text id="55">
<raw>
SYDNEY - A traveller who was hospitalised for tests because he felt unwell after arriving in Australia from Vietnam is unlikely to be suffering from bird flu, Australian health officials said today.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="56">
<raw>
"Health experts believe it is very unlikely that the diagnosis will be avian influenza," the New South Wales Health Department said in a statement.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="57">
<raw>
It said the unidentified person was recently in an area in Vietnam which had chickens and has had a previous influenza-like illness.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="58">
<raw>
Thai man dies of bird flu, official says
</raw>
</text>
<text id="59">
<raw>
BANGKOK - A 59-year-old Thai man has died of bird flu, the country's 17th victim of the H5N1 virus since it swept through much of Asia in late 2003, a senior Health Ministry official said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="60">
<raw>
The man died on August 10 in a northeastern province near the Lao border after chickens at his house fell sick and died, Kamnuan Ungchusak said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="61">
<raw>
He said the final laboratory tests were completed only last week.Bird flu still threat, says WHO director
</raw>
</text>
<text id="62">
<raw>
Bird flu remains a threat three years after scientists first raised alarms of a possible human pandemic, says the World Health Organisation's acting regional director.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="63">
<raw>
Dr Richard Nesbit, speaking yesterday on the eve of the WHO's 57th regional committee meeting in Auckland, said as long as the avian flu virus remained in the environment, its threat to human life could not be dismissed.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="64">
<raw>
Avian influenza and non-communicable diseases such as cancer will be among issues discussed when health officials from 27 countries meet at Aotea Centre today for the week-long meeting. Other items on the agenda include the emergence of multidrug resistant tuberculosis, prevention and control of HIV/Aids and the exodus of skilled health workers to wealthier countries.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="65">
<raw>
But bird flu remains an ever-present threat to the region since it reappeared in 2003, spreading to Europe, the Middle East and Africa and leading to the culling of millions of domestic poultry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="66">
<raw>
With new poultry outbreaks in Cambodia and Thailand and the virus still claiming lives in Indonesia, fears are that the disease will reappear across Asia and elsewhere in the cooler months of the northern hemisphere. "In our view, the risk of a pandemic continues unabated," said Dr Nesbit.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="67">
<raw>
 He was, however, encouraged by the progress in planning, citing that the last human case in Vietnam was in November last year. "Scattered outbreaks" in poultry and wild migrating birds were still likely, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="68">
<raw>
"As long as avian influenza is endemic in the environment, there is a risk of a human pandemic."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="69">
<raw>
The outbreak has infected 241 people and killed 141 around the world. Indonesia has had 60 cases and 46 deaths.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="70">
<raw>
Bird flu claims first human life in West Africa
</raw>
</text>
<text id="71">
<raw>
LAGOS (Reuters) - Nigeria confirmed the first human death from the H5N1 virus in sub-Saharan Africa on Wednesday after tests on a dead woman showed she had contracted bird flu. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="72">
<raw>
The 22-year-old died after feathering and disembowelling an infected chicken. She was from Lagos, the commercial capital of Africa's most populous country, Information Minister Frank Nweke said. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="73">
<raw>
Test on three other victims, one of them the woman's mother, were inconclusive. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="74">
<raw>
Nigeria was the first African nation to detect the H5N1 virus in poultry last year and had conducted tests on 14 people suspected of having the virus. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="75">
<raw>
Although bird flu remains essentially an animal disease, experts fear it could mutate into a form that could pass easily among humans, possibly killing millions. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="76">
<raw>
In Africa, 11 people have died in Egypt from bird flu since 2003 and there has been a single non-fatal human case in Djibouti, in the eastern Horn.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="77">
<raw>
The H5N1 virus has killed at least 164 people worldwide, most of them in Asia, and Indonesia has the world's highest death toll - 63. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="78">
<raw>
Six Indonesians have died in 2007 from bird flu, which is endemic in poultry in most of the country's provinces, and Planning Minister Paskah Suzetta said this flare-up meant bird flu would now be categorised as a national disaster. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="79">
<raw>
This will trigger additional funding for a focussed fight against the virus. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="80">
<raw>
"It is an epidemic, the funding will be allocated from a disaster fund in the state budget," Suzetta said on Wednesday. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="81">
<raw>
"The handling of this will no longer be on an ad hoc basis, but it will be done comprehensively." Indonesia said in December it planned to tackle the virus more forcefully and hoped to beat it by the end of 2007. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="82">
<raw>
Nigeria is among countries regarded by experts as the weakest links in the global attempt to stem infections of birds. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="83">
<raw>
The virus has spread to 17 of Nigeria's 36 states over the past year despite measures such as culling, quarantine and bans on transporting live poultry. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="84">
<raw>
World Health Organisation spokesman Gregory Hartl said a human case of bird flu in Nigeria was to be expected because of the experience in other countries, such as Indonesia, with huge poultry populations where chickens and hens live in close proximity to humans. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="85">
<raw>
"It does not change anything from a public health point of view," Hartl said. "It had to happen sooner or later." 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="86">
<raw>
In Japan, the Agriculture Ministry confirmed an outbreak of bird flu in the western prefecture of Okayama, the third in the country since the beginning of the year. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="87">
<raw>
Another outbreak is suspected at a poultry farm in the southwestern prefecture of Miyazaki. There have been no reported cases of human infection from the virus in Japan. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="88">
<raw>
More than 200 million birds have died from bird flu or have been killed to prevent its spread since 2003. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="89">
<raw>
New H5N1 outbreak confirmed in chickens in central Thailand 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="90">
<raw>
BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) — A fresh outbreak of the deadly H5N1 bird flu virus has been found in poultry in central Thailand, the livestock department said Thursday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="91">
<raw>
The outbreak was confirmed by laboratory tests after the deaths of a half-dozen chickens in a village Ang Thong province on Friday, said Nirand Uaebumrungsut, a veterinarian with the Agriculture Ministry's Department of Livestock Development.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="92">
<raw>
It was the second outbreak in just over a week, after authorities reported Jan. 23 that bird flu had been detected in hens in northeastern Thailand.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="93">
<raw>
FAO recommends Indonesia carry out blanket vaccination to contain bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="94">
<raw>
JAKARTA: The United Nations' Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) is recommending that Indonesia carry out blanket vaccination in districts which have high incidence of the bird flu virus in poultry. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="95">
<raw>
The FAO believes the increase in vaccination coverage will reduce the circulation of the virus which is already present in 30 out of 33 provinces in Indonesia. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="96">
<raw>
Despite measures taken to control the outbreak in the last three months, poultry and birds in Indonesia continue to be infected with the H5N1 virus. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="97">
<raw>
More humans are also being infected. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="98">
<raw>
Five human deaths since the start of the year brought the total number of fatalities in Indonesia to 63 - the highest in the world. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="99">
<raw>
The gravity of the situation prompted Indonesian authorities to ban backyard fowl in the capital and two other neighbouring provinces which are considered the worst-hit areas. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="100">
<raw>
However UN's Food and Agriculture Organization says that is not enough. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="101">
<raw>
James J McGrane, Avian Influenza Control Programme, FAO Indonesia, said: "It must be taken into account with the other elements such as surveillance, reporting, ring vaccination, bio-security and raising awareness among the general population." 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="102">
<raw>
Dr McGrane, who is working closely with the Indonesian authorities, says more districts in Indonesia must be included in the surveillance and reporting programme. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="103">
<raw>
The FAO is also advising Jakarta to take the fight to another level. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="104">
<raw>
"There's also probably a need now to modify strategy in terms of applying wider blanket vaccination in districts that have a high incidence of disease in poultry. And that is a strategy which we will be discussing with the Ministry of Agriculture in the near future and we're hoping for additional committed resources in order to implement wider-scale vaccination programme," said Dr McGrane. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="105">
<raw>
The FAO believes blanket vaccination will reduce the circulation of the virus, found mainly in Java, Lampung in Sumatra and the island of Bali. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="106">
<raw>
Experts say there is no quick fix in the battling of the bird flu virus in Indonesia. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="107">
<raw>
Banning backyard chickens is just a short-term measure. More time and effort will be needed to restructure Indonesia's poultry industry such as relocating commercial farms, slaughtering houses and bird markets away from residential areas. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="108">
<raw>
All these, experts predict, may take at least three years to accomplish. - CNA/so 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="109">
<raw>
31 - Poor sanitation blamed for diarrhea outbreak ....     
</raw>
</text>
<text id="110">
<raw>
Provincial  
</raw>
</text>
<text id="111">
<raw>
31 - Poor sanitation blamed for diarrhea outbreak spread in Bohol town; state of calamity declared
</raw>
</text>
<text id="112">
<raw>
A senior health official has blamed poor sanitation for spreading the diarrhea outbreak to four more barangays in Loon town, Bohol, bringing the total number of affected villages to 48.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="113">
<raw>
To date, the number of cases has reached over 400, including outpatients, and 48 of the 67 barangays in Loon are now affected, prompting the Bohol provincial government to declare a state of calamity.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="114">
<raw>
Dr. Cora Lou Kintanar of the Department of Health (DOH-7) local health assistance division, said the people themselves should practice proper sanitation to halt the spread of the disease.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="115">
<raw>
She advised that food should always be covered to protect it from flies, which are also considered carriers of the disease.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="116">
<raw>
Thorough washing of hands before handling food is also one of the initial steps that should be taken, she added.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="117">
<raw>
Kintanar said the outbreak actually started in November but Loon municipal health officials did not find the situation alarming because only a few cases were reported.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="118">
<raw>
Diarrhea cases increased in December although the DOH-7 received the alert only last week.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="119">
<raw>
"It is possible some could have been suffering it already and they got infected again because they did not receive instructions on how to maintain proper sanitation," Kintanar said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="120">
<raw>
She said the microorganism, Shifella flexneri, has an incubation period of 1-4 days and that for young children, the onset is sudden.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="121">
<raw>
"These episodes vary with increasing severity that sometimes the patients may experience nausea and vomiting and dehydration. But this could be resolved in only two weeks,' Kintanar said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="122">
<raw>
For severe cases, however, the illness could last up to six weeks.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="123">
<raw>
Kintanar warned that the "patients" who are recovering from the illness are considered carriers."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="124">
<raw>
Carriers are individuals that harbor specific pathogenic organisms who, though often immune to the agent harbored, may transmit the disease to others.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="125">
<raw>
The DOH-7 team, headed by Regional Director Dr. Susan Madarietta, is coordinating with Bohol Governor Erico Aumentado to discuss ways to contain the infection.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="126">
<raw>
Bohol provincial health officer Dr. Reymoses Cabagnot said they can only say the outbreak is under control if every one has been fully treated and no new cases are reported.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="127">
<raw>
Fifteen teams from DOH, Bohol provincial health office and local government attended the barangay assemblies in Loon Tuesday to disseminate proper waste disposal and the water chlorination process. (PNA) 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="128">
<raw>
Four suspected bird flu deaths in Nigeria
</raw>
</text>
<text id="129">
<raw>
22-year-old woman victim of H5N1 strain; tests on three others inconclusive
</raw>
</text>
<text id="130">
<raw>
LAGOS, Nigeria - Four Nigerians are suspected to have died from H5N1 bird flu, but tests on three of the victims were inconclusive and the virus was confirmed scientifically in only one case, a senior health official said on Wednesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="131">
<raw>
Abdulsalam Nasidi, a bird flu expert at the health ministry, said the three inconclusive cases were the mother of the confirmed case in Lagos, a poultry worker in northeastern Taraba state and one person in far northeastern Borno state.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="132">
<raw>
The woman from Nigeria’s commercial capital Lagos is the first confirmed human victim of bird flu in sub-Saharan Africa, after the deadly disease was first found in poultry in Nigeria a year ago.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="133">
<raw>
“Last night our team of 13 scientists were able to conclusively identify the case of avian influenza in a 22-year-old female who died in Lagos,” Nweke told a news conference.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="134">
<raw>
The woman was one of 14 people, three of whom died, from whom samples were taken for tests that were concluded on Tuesday. Samples are now being sent to foreign laboratories for confirmation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="135">
<raw>
Bird flu claims first human life in West Africa
</raw>
</text>
<text id="136">
<raw>
LAGOS - Nigeria confirmed the first human death from the H5N1 virus in sub-Saharan Africa on Wednesday after tests on a dead woman showed she had contracted bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="137">
<raw>
The 22-year-old died after feathering and disembowelling an infected chicken. She was from Lagos, the commercial capital of Africa's most populous country, Information Minister Frank Nweke said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="138">
<raw>
Test on three other victims, one of them the woman's mother, were inconclusive.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="139">
<raw>
Nigeria was the first African nation to detect the H5N1 virus in poultry last year and had conducted tests on 14 people suspected of having the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="140">
<raw>
Although bird flu remains essentially an animal disease, experts fear it could mutate into a form that could pass easily among humans, possibly killing millions.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="141">
<raw>
In Africa, 11 people have died in Egypt from bird flu since 2003 and there has been a single non-fatal human case in Djibouti, in the eastern Horn.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="142">
<raw>
The H5N1 virus has killed at least 164 people worldwide, most of them in Asia, and Indonesia has the world's highest death toll - 63.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="143">
<raw>
Six Indonesians have died in 2007 from bird flu, which is endemic in poultry in most of the country's provinces, and Planning Minister Paskah Suzetta said this flare-up meant bird flu would now be categorised as a national disaster.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="144">
<raw>
This will trigger additional funding for a focussed fight against the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="145">
<raw>
"It is an epidemic, the funding will be allocated from a disaster fund in the state budget," Suzetta said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="146">
<raw>
"The handling of this will no longer be on an ad hoc basis, but it will be done comprehensively." Indonesia said in December it planned to tackle the virus more forcefully and hoped to beat it by the end of 2007.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="147">
<raw>
Nigeria is among countries regarded by experts as the weakest links in the global attempt to stem infections of birds.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="148">
<raw>
The virus has spread to 17 of Nigeria's 36 states over the past year despite measures such as culling, quarantine and bans on transporting live poultry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="149">
<raw>
World Health Organisation spokesman Gregory Hartl said a human case of bird flu in Nigeria was to be expected because of the experience in other countries, such as Indonesia, with huge poultry populations where chickens and hens live in close proximity to humans.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="150">
<raw>
"It does not change anything from a public health point of view," Hartl said. "It had to happen sooner or later."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="151">
<raw>
In Japan, the Agriculture Ministry confirmed an outbreak of bird flu in the western prefecture of Okayama, the third in the country since the beginning of the year.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="152">
<raw>
Another outbreak is suspected at a poultry farm in the southwestern prefecture of Miyazaki. There have been no reported cases of human infection from the virus in Japan.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="153">
<raw>
More than 200 million birds have died from bird flu or have been killed to prevent its spread since 2003.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="154">
<raw>
Bird flu spreading again in Asia
</raw>
</text>
<text id="155">
<raw>
4 deaths reported in Indonesia; virus active in Vietnam and Thailand
</raw>
</text>
<text id="156">
<raw>
JAKARTA - An Indonesian hospital was on Monday overwhelmed with patients suffering bird flu symptoms as the disease spread further in Vietnam and Thailand reported its first case in poultry in six months.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="157">
<raw>
But farm ministry officials in Japan said there was no evidence of the disease spreading there following confirmation at the weekend of a bird flu outbreak at a poultry farm in the southwest in which 3,800 chickens died.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="158">
<raw>
A recent spurt of infections of the H5N1 bird flu virus, which re-emerged in Asia in late 2003, has alarmed health officials.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="159">
<raw>
Four Indonesians have already died this year after a six-week lull in cases, taking the number of human deaths from bird flu in the country to 61, the highest in the world.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="160">
<raw>
At Jakarta’s Persahabatan hospital, where doctors were treating 9 people with bird flu symptoms, including a 5-year-old girl in intensive care, its isolation wards were overwhelmed.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="161">
<raw>
“If we get more patients, we will send them to Sulianti Saroso,” Muchtar Ichsan, the head of the bird flu ward, told Reuters, referring the country’s main bird flu treatment center in North Jakarta.Egyptian woman tests positive for bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="162">
<raw>
27-year-old hospitalized since Jan. 13, health officials confirm
</raw>
</text>
<text id="163">
<raw>
CAIRO - A 27-year-old Egyptian woman tested positive for the deadly H5N1 bird flu virus, a World Health Organization official said on Wednesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="164">
<raw>
The virus has claimed 10 lives in Egypt while eight other positive cases recovered since it first surfaced in Egyptian poultry in February.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="165">
<raw>
“Unfortunately, yes there is a new case,” said Hassan el-Bushra, regional adviser for communicable diseases surveillance for the World Health Organization.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="166">
<raw>
He told Reuters tests carried out by Egyptian authorities were positive for the H5N1 virus and he was awaiting the results of a second set of tests.Indonesian teen dies from bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="167">
<raw>
2nd victim hospitalized; farmer in eastern China sick with virus
</raw>
</text>
<text id="168">
<raw>
JAKARTA - The World Health Organization (WHO) confirmed on Thursday the death of an Indonesian teenager from bird flu. A second Indonesian bird flu victim, a 37-year-old woman from Banten Province on Java island, was in hospital on Wednesday, WHO said. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="169">
<raw>
China said on Wednesday that a farmer from the eastern province of Anhui had contracted H5N1, the country's first human case in months. As in other human bird flu cases in China there was no reported poultry outbreak in the area, raising questions as to how he contracted the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="170">
<raw>
Separately, South Korea’s health ministry said on Thursday a poultry worker was infected with the H5N1 strain of bird flu late last year, but had not been seriously ill.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="171">
<raw>
Most human victims of bird flu have contracted the virus from infected birds, usually chickens, ducks or geese and there is usually a surge in cases during cooler months when the virus seems to thrive.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="172">
<raw>
The 37-year-old Chinese man from the eastern province of Anhui kept backyard birds, but as in other human bird flu cases in China there was no reported poultry outbreak in the area, raising questions as to how he contracted the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="173">
<raw>
The man developed symptoms of fever and pneumonia early last month and was discharged from hospital on Saturday, the state-run Health News said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="174">
<raw>
“In China, the challenge is now to identify where this virus is hiding and how it is circulating,” Henk Bekedam, the WHO’s China representative, told Reuters.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="175">
<raw>
China has reported 22 human cases, including 14 deaths, since 2003 and, with the world’s largest poultry population and millions of backyard birds roaming free, it is seen as a centre in the fight against the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="176">
<raw>
Bekedam said that as vaccination rates for birds improve in China, detecting avian influenza becomes harder and harder, offering a possible explanation for why there was no reported outbreak where the farmer lived.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="177">
<raw>
Bird flu suspected in chicken deaths in Japan
</raw>
</text>
<text id="178">
<raw>
Unclear whether humans infected on farm in southern part of country
</raw>
</text>
<text id="179">
<raw>
TOKYO - An outbreak of suspected bird flu has killed about 750 chickens on a farm on south Japan’s Kyushu island, a farm ministry official in Tokyo said on Thursday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="180">
<raw>
The farm, which has over 12,000 birds, is located in the small town of Kiyotake in Miyazaki Prefecture, an area devoted mainly to forestry and farming. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="181">
<raw>
The deaths occurred on Wednesday and Thursday, and if bird flu is confirmed, all the chickens on the farm will be destroyed, he said. It was not known if any humans were infected, he added.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="182">
<raw>
The farm will be placed in quarantine and local authorities are urging people to stay away from the area, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="183">
<raw>
Flu pandemic could kill up to 81 million people
</raw>
</text>
<text id="184">
<raw>
Deadly virus would have 'devastating impact' worldwide, new study finds
</raw>
</text>
<text id="185">
<raw>
LONDON - A flu virus as deadly as the one that caused the 1918 Spanish flu could kill as many as 81 million worldwide if it struck today, a new study estimates.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="186">
<raw>
By applying historical death rates to modern population data, the researchers calculated a death toll of 51 million to 81 million, with a median estimate of 62 million.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="187">
<raw>
That’s surprisingly high, said lead researcher Chris Murray of Harvard University. He did the analysis, in part, because he thought prior claims of 50 million deaths were wildly inflated.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="188">
<raw>
We expected to end up with a number between 15 and 20 million,” Murray said. “It turns out we were wrong.”
</raw>
</text>
<text id="189">
<raw>
The new work is published in Saturday’s issue of the journal The Lancet.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="190">
<raw>
The 1918 flu outbreak killed at least 40 million people worldwide. But flu pandemics have varied widely in their severity. The most recent, in 1957 and 1968, were relatively mild, killing 2 million and 1 million people worldwide respectively.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="191">
<raw>
To get their estimates, Murray and his colleagues examined all available death registration data from 1914 to 1923. There was sufficient information from 27 countries, including numbers from 24 U.S. states and nine provinces in India.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="192">
<raw>
The researchers compared death rates during the pandemic to average death rates before and after. That revealed how much the pandemic flu contributed to death rates, a figure called excess mortality. They then applied the excess mortality data to worldwide population data from 2004.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="193">
<raw>
If their median estimate of 62 million flu deaths occurred in a single year, the total number of deaths from all causes worldwide would more than double, jumping by 114 percent.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="194">
<raw>
Developing countries hardest-hit
</raw>
</text>
<text id="195">
<raw>
One surprise in the new study was the huge variation in how different countries would be affected by a pandemic. The study estimates that 96 percent of the deaths would occur in the developing world. Murray and colleagues noted there was a 30-fold or more variation in mortality.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="196">
<raw>
“That tells us it’s not just the genetic makeup of the virus that will cause deaths, but that there are a lot of other things that intervene,” he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="197">
<raw>
Determining the mitigating factors might help avert a catastrophe. “If we can answer that question, we may unlock the mysteries behind which non-pharmaceutical strategies could significantly decrease mortality,” said Murray.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="198">
<raw>
Population density, nutrition and immune status could all play roles, he suggests.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="199">
<raw>
“We know that even if we have much lower numbers of deaths worldwide than in 1918, the world will be severely stressed,” said Dr. Keiji Fukuda, coordinator of the World Health Organization’s Global Influenza Program. “Speculating about the possible numbers is an interesting exercise, but the really important thing is, what do we do about it?”
</raw>
</text>
<text id="200">
<raw>
Since the pandemic threat rose, with circulation of the H5N1 bird flu virus on a large scale in late 2003, the global community has bolstered its pandemic preparedness plans. Medical systems today are far stronger than they were last century, and the availability of antivirals and antibiotics — which did not exist in 1918 — should help greatly. Still, many of these advances remain out of reach for poor countries.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="201">
<raw>
'A devastating impact'
</raw>
</text>
<text id="202">
<raw>
Another question is the impact a flu pandemic would have on those infected with HIV. Seasonal influenza exacts a heavy toll on those with weakened immune systems. So, in the case of a new pandemic flu, Murray’s estimate might be optimistic.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="203">
<raw>
And while the Spanish flu often has been regarded as a worst-case scenario, there is no guarantee the next pandemic will not be even more deadly. Despite the tens of millions of deaths the 1918 flu caused, the death rate among those infected was approximately 2 percent. The fatality rate for the H5N1 virus is about 60 percent.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="204">
<raw>
However, experts think that if H5N1 were to evolve into a strain easily transmissible between people, it would also become less deadly.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="205">
<raw>
“It’s not in a virus’ interest to kill its hosts so readily, otherwise it can’t reproduce,” said Dr. Ian Gust, a flu expert at the University of Melbourne, Australia.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="206">
<raw>
Still, there is no guarantee that H5N1 would become less deadly.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="207">
<raw>
If it doesn’t, “we would be in for a devastating impact,” said Gust. “All bets would be off.”
</raw>
</text>
<text id="208">
<raw>
In Vietnam, bird flu has been confirmed in a fourth Vietnamese province after tests on 70 ducks showed they had died from the H5N1 virus, a government report said on Wednesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="209">
<raw>
The virus that first struck the delta region in late 2003 re-emerged last month. Vietnam has had no human H5N1 cases since November 2005.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="210">
<raw>
South Korea confirms outbreak of H5N1 bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="211">
<raw>
Case is the nation’s first in 3 years; ministry orders 236,000 poultry culled
</raw>
</text>
<text id="212">
<raw>
SEOUL - South Korea said on Saturday a bird flu outbreak at a poultry farm was caused by the highly virulent H5N1 strain of the virus, in the country's first case for three years of the infection that can kill humans.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="213">
<raw>
The Agriculture Ministry said earlier this week it suspected bird flu had killed 6,000 chickens at a farm in the southwest of the country that lies on a path for migratory birds.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="214">
<raw>
"It is the H5N1 strain," a ministry official said by telephone on Saturday, after test results.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="215">
<raw>
The ministry ordered the culling of 236,000 poultry within a 1,640-foot radius of the farm in North Cholla province about 100 miles from Seoul, a ministry statement said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="216">
<raw>
Quarantine authorities also banned the shipment of more than 5 million poultry from 221 farms within a 6.2-mile radius of the farm.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="217">
<raw>
No people appear infected
</raw>
</text>
<text id="218">
<raw>
There were no reports to suggest local residents or quarantine officials had been infected, another Agriculture Ministry official said by telephone.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="219">
<raw>
Between December 2003 and March 2004, about 400,000 poultry at South Korean farms were infected by bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="220">
<raw>
During that outbreak, the country culled 5.3 million birds and spent about $1.6 billion on preventing the disease spreading, officials said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="221">
<raw>
Subsequent testing in the United States indicated at least nine South Korean workers involved in the cull had been infected with the H5N1 virus, but none developed major illnesses.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="222">
<raw>
Since 2003, outbreaks have been confirmed in around 50 countries and territories, according to the World Organization for Animal Health.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="223">
<raw>
North Korea had an outbreak at poultry farms near the capital Pyongyang in February 2005, which led it to cull more than 200,000 chickens and vaccinate 1.1 million poultry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="224">
<raw>
The World Health Organization said that by Nov. 13, there had been 258 cases of human infection of the H5N1 strain since 2003, killing 153 people. Many of the victims were Asians, with 98 deaths in Vietnam and Indonesia, WHO said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="225">
<raw>
Indonesian woman dies of bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="226">
<raw>
67-year-old is the country's 54th death from virus
</raw>
</text>
<text id="227">
<raw>
JAKARTA - A 67-year-old Indonesian woman died of bird flu after being treated at a hospital for more than a week, marking the country’s 54th death from the virus, an official at the health ministry said on Monday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="228">
<raw>
“The virus in her was highly pathogenic, very vicious. She is the 54th casualty out of 71 cases,” said Runizar Ruesin, the head of the health ministry’s bird flu information centre.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="229">
<raw>
The woman from the West Java city of Bandung died on Sunday night, the official said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="230">
<raw>
Hadi Yusuf, the doctor who treated her, told Reuters the disease also affected the woman’s kidneys.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="231">
<raw>
Tests last week found she had the H5N1 virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="232">
<raw>
Indonesia has become one of the frontlines in the battle against the disease. No country has suffered from more deaths than this huge Asian country of 17,000 islands where millions of chickens roam backyards freely.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="233">
<raw>
Despite the rise in the human death toll, the Indonesian government has resisted mass culling of birds, citing the expense and impracticality in a sprawling, populous country where many people are still unperturbed by the bird flu threat.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="234">
<raw>
Diseases such as malaria, dengue fever and tuberculosis kill thousands of Indonesians annually.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="235">
<raw>
Scientists plan new tactic to combat flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="236">
<raw>
Scientists say they have identified a weakness in a protein in influenza viruses which could be targeted by new drugs to halt the spread of infection.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="237">
<raw>
The protein's long tail appears to be its weak point. The tail loop is almost identical in different strains of influenza A - the most common form of the virus. New drugs that target it could be effective against multiple strains including the feared H5N1 bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="238">
<raw>
"We have determined the atomic structure of the nucleoprotein from influenza A virus and found it contains a flexible tail loop," said Dr Yizhi Jane Tao, head of the research team from Rice University in Houston, Texas.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="239">
<raw>
"This protein is important for virus replication. The tail structure gives us some hints about how to design antiviral drugs by using this protein as a target."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="240">
<raw>
The scientists are now collaborating with other researchers to screen possible drug compounds that could inhibit virus replication.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="241">
<raw>
The findings reported in the journal Nature could pave the way for a totally new approach to a virus that can kill.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="242">
<raw>
 Current treatment is centred on antiviral drugs such as Roche's Tamiflu, which Governments around the world have stockpiled against a potential pandemic. Some H5N1 viruses have shown resistance to the drug.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="243">
<raw>
Health experts fear H5N1, which has infected 258 people and killed 154 since late 2003, could mutate into a form that could become highly infectious in humans, sparking a pandemic in which millions could die.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="244">
<raw>
Regular seasonal influenza, type A and type B, kills between 250,000 and 500,000 people a year globally, says the World Health Organisation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="245">
<raw>
Dr Tao and scientists at the University of Texas at Austin grew nucleoprotein (NP) crystals on glass slides sealed in a jar.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="246">
<raw>
NP has several important functions and is central to viral infection because after the virus has hijacked a cell, the protein forms columns that are needed for the virus to infect other cells.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="247">
<raw>
The tail loop of NP has about 30 amino acids, which are the building blocks of proteins.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="248">
<raw>
"We found that a mutation in only one residue out of 30 was enough to prevent the NPs from coming together to form the building blocks for the columns," Dr Tao said, "and without these columns the virus cannot make copies and infect other cells."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="249">
<raw>
Indonesia probes possible bird flu cluster
</raw>
</text>
<text id="250">
<raw>
2 siblings hospitalized after 25-year-old man's death
</raw>
</text>
<text id="251">
<raw>
JAKARTA - Indonesia is investigating a possible cluster of bird flu cases after a man died and his brother and sister were hospitalized, one of them testing positive for bird flu, a doctor said on Tuesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="252">
<raw>
The man, 25, died on Sunday with bird flu symptoms after being treated at a Christian hospital in Bandung, the capital of West Java province, said Hadi Yusuf, head of the bird flu ward at the city’s Hasan Sadikin hospital.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="253">
<raw>
The dead man’s brother, 20, and sister, 15, were being treated in Hasan Sadikin hospital and tests carried out by a government laboratory showed the surviving brother had bird flu, Yusuf said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="254">
<raw>
It was not clear if samples from the dead brother had been taken for tests when he was treated, the doctor said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="255">
<raw>
“The condition of the (other) brother is not good. He’s on a ventilator,” Yusuf told Reuters by telephone.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="256">
<raw>
Results for the girl were expected on Wednesday, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="257">
<raw>
The brothers often bought dead chickens to feed their dog, but the girl had no known history of contact with chickens, the doctor said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="258">
<raw>
“If it is true that the youngest did not touch chickens at all and she had bird flu, we need to suspect she got it from the brothers,” he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="259">
<raw>
According to the World Health Organization (WHO), 146 of the 249 people confirmed as infected with H5N1 bird flu have died since 2003.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="260">
<raw>
Those infected have come from countries ranging from China to Iraq to Djibouti. Indonesia, with 51 deaths, has the highest toll of any nation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="261">
<raw>
 • Facts not fears
</raw>
</text>
<text id="262">
<raw>
Questions and answers about avian influenza 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="263">
<raw>
In Thailand, a 59-year-old man died of bird flu last month, the country’s 17th victim of the virus since it swept through much of Asia in late 2003, a senior Health Ministry official said on Tuesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="264">
<raw>
The man died on Aug. 10 in a northeastern province near the Lao border after chickens at his house fell sick and died, the official said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="265">
<raw>
The virus mainly affects birds but experts fear it could mutate into a strain capable of killing millions of people in a global pandemic.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="266">
<raw>
This fear heightened in May when seven people in an extended family died of bird flu in Indonesia’s North Sumatra province.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="267">
<raw>
The WHO has said limited human-to-human transmission is highly likely to have occurred in the Sumatra cases but that the transmission was not sustainable and occurred only during close, prolonged contact, such as a parent looking after an infected child.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="268">
<raw>
Indonesia has been criticized for not doing enough to combat the disease, endemic in birds in most of the provinces in the archipelago of 17,000 islands, the world’s largest.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="269">
<raw>
The United Nations bird flu coordinator, David Nabarro, said this month that Indonesia had made progress in its fight against bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="270">
<raw>
But he expressed disappointment at the slow flow of funds pledged by international donors to Indonesia for the effort.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="271">
<raw>
Health experts and scientists say it is crucial to control the virus from spreading in poultry to limit the chances of more people contracting the disease. The more it spreads, the greater the risks of the virus mutating into a form that can easily pass between humans.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="272">
<raw>
Indonesian boy dies of bird flu, official says
</raw>
</text>
<text id="273">
<raw>
Nine-year-old's death brings country's toll to 51
</raw>
</text>
<text id="274">
<raw>
JAKARTA - A nine-year-old Indonesian boy has died of bird flu, an official of the health ministry’s bird flu information center said on Sunday, taking the country’s death toll from the disease to 51.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="275">
<raw>
The boy died on Friday at a hospital in Jakarta, Runizar Ruesin, the head of the center, told Reuters by phone.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="276">
<raw>
“The result came out this morning. It has been confirmed positive,” he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="277">
<raw>
The boy, a resident of Ciputat Raya in South Jakarta, had suffered from fever, cough, runny nose and pneumonia after he began to get sick on Sept. 13, Ruesin said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="278">
<raw>
The boy was said to have had contact with a sick bird. Most human cases are known to have followed such contacts.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="279">
<raw>
His death comes after the health ministry said on Friday that bird flu killed an 11-year-old boy from East Java province. The boy died last week after chickens died around his house. The ministry said it was sending a team to investigate the case.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="280">
<raw>
Highest number of deaths in Indonesia
</raw>
</text>
<text id="281">
<raw>
Indonesia has the highest bird flu death toll of any nation. Not including the deaths of the two boys, the H5N1 avian flu virus has killed 144 people worldwide, the World Health Organization says.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="282">
<raw>
The virus mainly affects birds but experts fear it could mutate into a strain capable of killing millions of people in a global pandemic.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="283">
<raw>
Indonesia has been criticized for not doing enough to combat the disease, endemic in birds in most of the provinces in the archipelago of 17,000 islands, the world’s largest.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="284">
<raw>
The United Nations bird flu coordinator, David Nabarro, said this month that Indonesia had made progress in its fight against bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="285">
<raw>
But he expressed disappointment at the slow flow of funds pledged by international donors to Indonesia for the effort.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="286">
<raw>
Avian influenza - situation in Nigeria - update
</raw>
</text>
<text id="287">
<raw>
3 February 2007
</raw>
</text>
<text id="288">
<raw>
The government of Nigeria has announced today the presence of A/H5N1 avian influenza virus in a 22-year-old deceased female from Lagos. The initial positive test findings from a laboratory in Nigeria were confirmed by the WHO Collaborating Centre for Reference and Research on Influenza in London (see previous report). Further investigations are under way to identify the source of her infection.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="289">
<raw>
All samples from contacts of the deceased have tested negative by the WHO Collaborating Centre.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="290">
<raw>
H5N1 virus has been identified in poultry outbreaks in Nigeria and similar to other affected countries, sporadic cases of human infection with avian influenza are not unexpected. WHO is working with the government of Nigeria to carry out intensive surveillance and reports of additional suspected cases may occur as people with influenza-like symptoms seek medical advice.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="291">
<raw>
The H5N1 avian influenza virus is not transmitted to humans through properly prepared and cooked food. Cases of human infection with H5N1 have frequently been linked to the home slaughter and subsequent handling of diseased or dead birds prior to cooking. These practices represent the highest risk to human infection and are the most important to avoid. When handling raw poultry or live or dead birds, it is imperative to disinfect hands and surfaces with soap and water. Consumers also need to be sure that during the cooking process, poultry reaches temperatures of at least 70?C in all parts and that eggs are fully cooked throughout. Detailed recommendations concerning food safety are available here.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="292">
<raw>
Meningococcal disease in the Democratic Republic of the Congo
</raw>
</text>
<text id="293">
<raw>
2 February 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="294">
<raw>
From 1 January to 31 January 2007, the Ministry of Health has reported 53 suspected cases including 6 deaths (case-fatality rate, 11.3%) in Adi health zone, Province Orientale, in the north-eastern part of the country, bordering Uganda. Two cerebrospinal fluid specimens have tested positive for Neisseria meningitidis serogroup A by latex test.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="295">
<raw>
A vaccination campaign targeting 99 400 people is being prepared and will be synchronized with Uganda, which is currently experiencing an outbreak of meningococcal disease in the neighbouring area. The International Coordinating Group (ICG) on Vaccine Provision for Epidemic Meningitis Control has agreed to provide 115 830 doses of bivalent meningococcal vaccine (A/C) along with injection materials and oily chloramphenicol. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="296">
<raw>
WHO and M?decins sans Fronti?res, Switzerland are working with the Ministry of Health to contain the outbreak. Case management, community education and strengthened surveillance are continuing.Avian influenza - situation in Nigeria
</raw>
</text>
<text id="297">
<raw>
31 January 2007
</raw>
</text>
<text id="298">
<raw>
The government of Nigeria has announced the death from suspected avian influenza infection in a 22-year-old female from Lagos. She died on 16 January 2007. The mother of the 22-year-old died on 4 January with similar symptoms.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="299">
<raw>
Preliminary tests on the samples from the 22-year-old were positive for influenza A/H5. Samples have now been sent to a WHO Collaborating Centre for Reference and Research on Influenza for confirmation. Results are expected shortly. No samples were taken from the mother.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="300">
<raw>
Contacts have been followed up and have shown no symptoms at twice the incubation period for avian influenza infection. Samples have been tested from these contacts as well as from three other suspected cases, including one fatal case and have all been negative in preliminary tests. These samples have also been sent to a WHO Collaborating Centre for Reference and Research on Influenza.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="301">
<raw>
It is important to reiterate that properly cooked poultry meat is safe to consume when cooked at temperatures at or above 70?C in all parts, until none of the meat is red. There is no epidemiological evidence to indicate that people have been infected with H5N1 virus following consumption of properly cooked poultry or eggs. The greatest risk of exposure to the virus is through the slaughter and handling of live or already dead infected poultry. More detailed recommendations can be found here.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="302">
<raw>
WHO is working with the government of Nigeria to monitor the situation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="303">
<raw>
Rift Valley Fever in Kenya and Somalia - update 3
</raw>
</text>
<text id="304">
<raw>
31 January 2007
</raw>
</text>
<text id="305">
<raw>
Kenya
</raw>
</text>
<text id="306">
<raw>
As of 30 January 2007, 411 suspected cases, including 121 deaths (case-fatality rate, 29%) have been reported in North Eastern Province, Coast Province, Eastern Province and Central Province (see map). One hundred and thirty-one cases have been laboratory confirmed.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="307">
<raw>
The North Eastern Province has been the most affected, with Garissa district (175 suspected cases, 58 confirmed cases, including 57 deaths) and Ijara district (125 suspected cases and 22 confirmed cases, including 23 deaths) reporting the most cases and deaths. Sporadic cases have also been reported from districts in Eastern Province (Isiolo - 8 suspected cases, 3 confirmed cases) and from districts in Central Province (Kirinyanga - 4 suspected cases, 4 confirmed cases, including 1 death; Kajiado - 3 suspected cases, 1 confirmed case, including 3 deaths; Maragua - 1 suspected case, 1 confirmed case); Thika - 2 suspected cases, 1 confirmed case). Some of the cases from Central Province were diagnosed in Nairobi.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="308">
<raw>
The outbreak appears to be in decline, although the Ministry of Health continues to coordinate activities to contain the outbreak, including active surveillance. The team from the Global Outbreak Alert and Response Network (see previous report) has returned from the affected areas, having provided a mobile laboratory for initial diagnosis of the disease, training in case management/infection control to provincial health officials and assistance with health education and informing affected communities about the disease. WHO, the Ministry of Health and the Ministry of Livestock and Fisheries Development developed key public health messages which have been disseminated in the local community, and meetings were held with community religious leaders.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="309">
<raw>
Somalia
</raw>
</text>
<text id="310">
<raw>
As of 30 January 2007, WHO has reported 100 suspected cases, including 48 deaths, in Somalia (see map) with 1 case laboratory confirmed by the Kenyan Institute of Medical Research (KEMRI) and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention/ International Emerging Infectious Program (CDC/EIP) in Kenya. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="311">
<raw>
M?decins sans Fronti?res is facilitating transport of samples and the WHO country office has held training sessions with Somali medical officers on how to detect and contain the disease. However, the deteriorating security situation continues to hamper control measures in the affected area.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="312">
<raw>
Breaking News
</raw>
</text>
<text id="313">
<raw>
New E. coli outbreaks traced to fast food restaurants
</raw>
</text>
<text id="314">
<raw>
Officials believe shredded iceberg lettuce may be to blame for the outbreak.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="315">
<raw>
by Pam Rothman
</raw>
</text>
<text id="316">
<raw>
IDN Assistant Editor
</raw>
</text>
<text id="317">
<raw>
January 2007
</raw>
</text>
<text id="318">
<raw>
A recent outbreak of Escherichia coli O157:H7 in the Northeast was traced to Taco Bell restaurants in that area, according to health officials from the CDC. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="319">
<raw>
According to the FDA, the outbreak was first reported in New Jersey on Nov. 20, 2006. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="320">
<raw>
Over the course of the next three weeks, the outbreak resulted in the illnesses of 33 people in New Jersey, 22 people in New York, 13 people in Pennsylvania, two people in Delaware and one person from South Carolina who ate at a Pennsylvania restaurant. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="321">
<raw>
Also on the same day as the initial report, all 15 Taco Bell restaurants in Philadelphia were closed voluntarily. Other Taco Bells in New Jersey and New York also closed. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="322">
<raw>
However, Taco Bells in Long Island and two of three restaurants in New Jersey that were implicated in the outbreak reopened. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="323">
<raw>
Outbreak over
</raw>
</text>
<text id="324">
<raw>
On Dec. 14, the CDC announced that the outbreak “appeared to be over.” However, CDC officials said additional cases could still be identified. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="325">
<raw>
By Dec. 14, 71 cases had been reported to the CDC, 53 (75%) people were hospitalized and eight (11%) were diagnosed with hemolytic uremic syndrome. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="326">
<raw>
To investigate the outbreak, federal health officials obtained samples of cilantro, cheddar cheese, blended cheese, green onions, yellow onions, tomatoes and lettuce from Taco Bell restaurants in the Northeast. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="327">
<raw>
The CDC issued a report on Dec. 6, noting that white onions tested positive for a different strain of E. coli than the one involved in the outbreak. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="328">
<raw>
Preliminary testing by independent labs indicated green onions as the culprit, and as a result of that report, Taco Bell officials removed green onions from their 5,800 restaurants nationwide. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="329">
<raw>
Although the investigation is ongoing, officials now believe that shredded iceberg lettuce may have been the cause of the outbreak. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="330">
<raw>
A CDC report said that shredded iceberg lettuce was “most likely to have been the vehicle of pathogen transmission in this outbreak.” 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="331">
<raw>
Distribution investigated
</raw>
</text>
<text id="332">
<raw>
Northeast Taco Bell restaurants receive their ingredients from a southern New Jersey distribution center located in Burlington County operated by McLane Food Service, which is based in Carrollton, Texas. The products from McLane that were shipped to New Jersey, including onions, cilantro, tomatoes and lettuce, were tested for E. coli. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="333">
<raw>
Health officials also tested produce from Ready Pac Produce, located in Florence, N.J., and based in California. Ready Pac is an additional produce processor that distributes to Taco Bell and was also involved in the E. coli outbreak in September involving spinach. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="334">
<raw>
Ready Pac purchased onions from Boskovich Farms, a California-based producer, according to Steve Dickstein, vice president for marketing at Ready Pac Produce. These particular onions were produced only for Taco Bell. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="335">
<raw>
“It certainly heightens concern and undermines confidence among consumers and buyers about the safety of products coming from [California],” said Trevor Suslow, PhD, vegetable specialist from the University of California, Davis. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="336">
<raw>
The FDA suggested that if consumers believe they were infected with E. coli or ate at Taco Bell between Nov. 20 and Dec. 6, they should contact their physician immediately.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="337">
<raw>
Another outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="338">
<raw>
A second outbreak of E. coli was traced to another fast food chain in Iowa and Minnesota. In this outbreak, approximately 40 people became ill and 18 people were hospitalized from eating at Taco John’s restaurants in Cedar Falls, Iowa and in Albert Lea and Austin, Minn. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="339">
<raw>
Federal health officials said this outbreak was not believed to be associated with the Taco Bell outbreak. Taco John’s has no association to Taco Bell and is based in Cheyenne, Wyo. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="340">
<raw>
Taco John’s closed briefly to replace the contaminated food with new food. Roma Foods located in Rice, Minn., is the main supplier for Taco John’s. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="341">
<raw>
British Bird Flu Is Asian Strain Of H5N1 Virus
</raw>
</text>
<text id="342">
<raw>
The Department for the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (DEFRA) has confirmed that the highly pathogenic Asian strain of the H5N1 virus was the one that killed 2,600 turkeys at a farm in Suffolk, England. Authorities say the outbreak is being contained and the threat to human health is negligible. The virus is similar to the one found in southern Hungary last month, where 3,000 geese were killed in a farm in Szentes.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="343">
<raw>
European Union agreed controls have been enforced, these include:
</raw>
</text>
<text id="344">
<raw>
-- Setting up a protection zone with a 3 kilometer radius around the infected area
</raw>
</text>
<text id="345">
<raw>
-- Setting up a surveillance zone with a 10 kilometer radius around the infected area
</raw>
</text>
<text id="346">
<raw>
So far, 164 people are known to have died of H5N1 infection worldwide since 2003, the majority of them in Asia. Over 220 million birds have either died of infection, or been killed in preventative measures, since 2003.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="347">
<raw>
Containing the spread of any outbreak is crucial in the battle to stop/delay the virus from mutating into a human transmissible form - something scientists fear will eventually happen.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="348">
<raw>
At the moment it is still very hard for a human to catch the illness from a bird. It is even harder for a human to infect another human.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="349">
<raw>
One of the ways in which the H5N1 virus could mutate would be to infect a person who has the normal human flu. The bird flu virus could then exchange genetic information with the human flu virus and acquire its ability to become easily human transmissible (spread easily from human-to-human).
</raw>
</text>
<text id="350">
<raw>
Basically, if fewer outbreaks among birds occur, fewer people become infected. If fewer people become infected, the chances of a mutation are smaller.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="351">
<raw>
H5N1 Killed 2600 Poultry In England
</raw>
</text>
<text id="352">
<raw>
Article Date: 03 Feb 2007 - 9:00 PST
</raw>
</text>
<text id="353">
<raw>
Both British and European Authorities have confirmed that the bird flu which killed 2,600 turkeys at a Bernard Matthews farm in Suffolk, East Anglia, England, was of the H5N1 strain. The remaining 150,000 turkeys on the farm will be slaughtered, say authorities. Further tests are being carried out to find out whether this H5N1 is the same strain as the Asian one.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="354">
<raw>
This is the first case of H5N1 infection in a British farm. Experts believe the turkeys caught bird flu from wild birds. As the turkeys were very young, none of them had entered the food chain, said the Bernard Matthews company. A spokesman for DEFRA said no produce had left the farm. Everyone who works on the farm will be given Tamiflu, an anti-viral drug.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="355">
<raw>
The farm, about 27 km south-west of Lowestoft, is now within a three-kilometre protection zone, a further 10 kilometer radius has been set up as a 'surveillance zone'.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="356">
<raw>
Authorities stressed that the infection only affected turkeys - there is currently no threat to human health.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="357">
<raw>
Peter Kendall, President, National Farmers' Union (NFU), in a BBC interview said all the focus will now be on eradicating this outbreak. He said the NFU will make sure they get the message across about how well this will be managed and controlled. He added that all farmers must be extremely vigilant and check their flocks carefully. Kendall said poultry is still safe to eat in the UK.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="358">
<raw>
For a period several bird events and sports will not be allowed in England, such as pigeon racing and bird shows.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="359">
<raw>
Comment by Editor of Medical News Today
</raw>
</text>
<text id="360">
<raw>
The British press will be going through everything with a fine tooth-comb. This will be a real test for the authorities. Any mistakes, or examples of incompetence will be published at lightning speed.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="361">
<raw>
The following European Union countries have now been affected by bird flu:
</raw>
</text>
<text id="362">
<raw>
Austria, Czech Rep, Denmark, France, Germany, Greece, Italy, Hungary, Poland, Slovakia, Slovenia, Sweden and the UK.Britain probes bird flu outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="363">
<raw>
POSTED: 4:57 a.m. EST, February 3, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="364">
<raw>
LONDON, England -- Britain was Saturday investigating a outbreak of bird flu at a poultry that has killed more than 2,000 turkeys.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="365">
<raw>
The Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs said that preliminary tests had confirmed the bird flu outbreak was the H5 strain of the disease.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="366">
<raw>
Further tests were underway to ascertain whether the birds were suffering from the H5N1 strain that can be fatal to humans.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="367">
<raw>
The disease struck at a farm in Suffolk, southeast England, run by poultry produce manufacturer Bernard Matthews, the UK Press Association reported.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="368">
<raw>
Officials said staff at the farm were being monitored and restrictions were in force to stop birds being moved in or out of the site, DEFRA said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="369">
<raw>
The outbreak is the second time in less than 12 months that UK-reared poultry has been hit by bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="370">
<raw>
More than 30,000 birds were slaughtered after chickens near Dereham, Norfolk, tested positive in April. One worker at the farm caught the disease and was treated for an eye infection.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="371">
<raw>
But the country has so far escaped major outbreaks of the deadly form of the disease, despite several incidents in eastern Europe.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="372">
<raw>
In May 2006, a wild swan carrying H5N1 was discovered dead in Scotland.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="373">
<raw>
Complacency undermines efforts against bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="374">
<raw>
BAMAKO - Experts fighting bird flu around the world met today to replenish their war chest and plot the next stage of their campaign to control the disease and avert a devastating human flu pandemic.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="375">
<raw>
The three-day meeting in Mali, the fourth global bird flu summit since late last year, includes a donor conference on Saturday seeking an extra US$1.2 billion ($1.74 billion) to US$1.5 billion ($2,18 billion) over 2-3 years to add to US$1.9 billion ($2,76 billion) pledged in Beijing last January.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="376">
<raw>
But the meeting began with a warning that complacency threatened to undermine international efforts against bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="377">
<raw>
"Technical experts are sometimes accused of having overestimated the risks from this disease, or of exaggerating its potential threat," said Modibo Traore, head of the African Union's InterAfrican Bureau for Animal Resources.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="378">
<raw>
"The rampant demotivation that has resulted seems to have affected the main players in the struggle on all continents, and notably the donor community," Traore told the opening session.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="379">
<raw>
 The outbreak of highly pathogenic H5N1 avian influenza began in Asia in 2003 and spread rapidly in early 2006.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="380">
<raw>
It has been detected in more than 50 countries around the world, including eight in Africa, where experts fear veterinary and human health systems are inadequate to contain outbreaks.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="381">
<raw>
"It's not a lot of money: US$500 million per year, divided by the population of Africa is less than a dollar each a year," United Nations influenza coordinator David Nabarro told Reuters in the Malian capital Bamako.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="382">
<raw>
So far the virus has killed 154 people who came into contact with sick birds and there are 258 reported cases worldwide.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="383">
<raw>
But worse than the devastating effects on vital poultry industries in poor and densely populated countries, scientists fear the virus could mutate to jump between humans, triggering a human flu pandemic that could kill millions of people.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="384">
<raw>
"The potential costs of an influenza pandemic would be of the order of US$1-2 trillion ... and the actual cost of avian influenza thus far has been in the multiple billions of dollars," Nabarro said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="385">
<raw>
Ordinary flu kills around 250,000 people around the world each year, but every 20 years or so the virus changes enough to cause a much more deadly pandemic -- the worst in living memory being "Spanish influenza" which killed anywhere from 20 million to 100 million people in 1918 at the end of World War 1.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="386">
<raw>
The last pandemic was in 1968 and experts say another pandemic could happen any time.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="387">
<raw>
"There is still a danger and the best solution is to finish with the virus in animals," said Bernard Vallat, director general of the World Organisation for Animal Health (OIE).
</raw>
</text>
<text id="388">
<raw>
Scientists say that is most likely to happen in Asia, which has the most infections, but Africa remains a weak link due to poor veterinary and public health services which are likely to give infections more time to spread before being detected.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="389">
<raw>
"The resources need to be mobilised and they need to be targeted at the countries at risk," said Ok Pannenborg, senior health advisor at the World Bank.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="390">
<raw>
The UN's Nabarro was upbeat, saying with the right advice and support African countries could step up their controls to combat bird flu -- and that rich nations would be prepared to foot the US$500 million-a-year bill.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="391">
<raw>
"Yes, I think the money will be pledged, because I think the world cares," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="392">
<raw>
Rash of child flu deaths under study
</raw>
</text>
<text id="393">
<raw>
POSTED: 4:21 a.m. EST, February 2, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="394">
<raw>
WASHINGTON (Reuters) -- Nine children have died of flu this season in Alabama, an unusually high number that has some experts worried, a pediatrician said Thursday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="395">
<raw>
Dr. Richard Whitley of the University of Alabama at Birmingham said he had sent samples from the children to the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention for analysis.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="396">
<raw>
"Nine children and we are a state of 4 million people," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="397">
<raw>
They were all affected with the regular seasonal flu, Whitley said in an interview, but were unusually ill with it.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="398">
<raw>
"We have tried extravagant things (to save them)."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="399">
<raw>
"These kids are presenting with an ARDS-like syndrome," he said. Acute respiratory distress syndrome usually occurs only with severe infections and is not normally a symptom of influenza.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="400">
<raw>
Normal seasonal influenza does kill children every year, even previously healthy children. Public health officials are watching flu more closely than before because of fears the H5N1 bird flu virus, a strain found primarily in birds but that has killed 164 people since 2003, might mutate into a fast-spreading and lethal pandemic form.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="401">
<raw>
"Unfortunately, it is not unusual for there to be pediatric deaths in any flu season," CDC director Dr. Julie Gerberding told reporters.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="402">
<raw>
It takes years sometimes to get good estimates, but 153 children died in the 2003-2004 flu season, according to CDC figures. This year so far the CDC had reported eight deaths among children, but its statistics are usually several weeks old.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="403">
<raw>
Whitley said his hospital started filling up with cases, mostly children, in December. The U.S. flu season normally runs from October to March.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="404">
<raw>
"Our hospital has been at 115 percent occupancy," Whitley told reporters.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="405">
<raw>
"We are not seeing influenza in our adult populations."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="406">
<raw>
Most of the 36,000 Americans who die of flu and flu-related pneumonia in an average year are elderly.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="407">
<raw>
Whitley said the annual flu wave was now on the wane in Alabama, but increased activity had been reported east, in South Carolina, and north in Illinois. The CDC says flu activity in the United States has not reached epidemic levels.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="408">
<raw>
"We do know that the majority of virus circulating in this flu season is a strain that is an excellent match to the vaccine," Gerberding said. Every year, the flu vaccine is reformulated with three strains of flu that match the most common types in circulation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="409">
<raw>
The CDC now recommends that most people in the United States get flu vaccines every year, including young children, people over the age of 50, health care workers and people with chronic conditions such as diabetes.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="410">
<raw>
Indonesia to declare H5N1 disaster
</raw>
</text>
<text id="411">
<raw>
POSTED: 10:38 p.m. EST, January 31, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="412">
<raw>
JAKARTA, Indonesia (AP) -- Indonesia will declare bird flu a national disaster, giving the government access to special funds to combat the disease that has killed 63 people nationwide, the planning minister said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="413">
<raw>
"It has become an epidemic," Paskah Suzetta told reporters on Wednesday in Jakarta, where authorities were preparing for the compulsory slaughter of thousands of backyard chickens as part of high-profile efforts to fight the H5N1 bird flu virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="414">
<raw>
"The president has indicated he will declare it a national disaster so money can be allocated from the state budget's disaster fund," Suzetta said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="415">
<raw>
Indonesia, which has tallied more than a third of the world's human deaths from H5N1, has come under criticism for failing to crack down on bird flu when it first appeared in poultry stocks nearly four years ago.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="416">
<raw>
The virus is now endemic in chickens almost all over the country and, despite optimism late last year that it may have been contained, it killed six people in the last month.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="417">
<raw>
Many of the 63 people who have died lived near the teeming capital, home also to more than 100,000 backyard chickens, ducks, doves and song birds.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="418">
<raw>
Authorities gave residents weeks to voluntarily get rid of their birds and were set to go door-to-door in some neighborhoods on Thursday to make sure the order had been carried out, Jakarta Governor Sutiyoso said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="419">
<raw>
"I will show no tolerance," he said after meeting with mayors, health and husbandry officials. "Chickens found running loose will be immediately killed, the sick ones thrown into a fire and the healthy ones given to owners to be fried and eaten."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="420">
<raw>
The effectiveness of the slaughter campaign remains to be seen, however, amid fears that many residents will hide their birds or that corrupt officials will be susceptible to bribes. The crackdown will also have to reach well beyond the capital.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="421">
<raw>
Past efforts to carry out mass slaughters have failed in part because the cash-strapped government said it could not afford to compensate bird owners. By declaring the disease a national disaster, it would no longer have such an excuse.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="422">
<raw>
Bird flu remains hard for humans to catch. But international experts fear it may mutate into a form that could spread easily between humans and potentially kill millions around the world.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="423">
<raw>
Indonesia is seen as a potential hotspot for that to happen.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="424">
<raw>
Japan confirms 2nd case of H5N1
</raw>
</text>
<text id="425">
<raw>
POSTED: 2:02 a.m. EST, January 27, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="426">
<raw>
TOKYO, Japan (Reuters) -- An outbreak of bird flu at a poultry farm in southwestern Japan was caused by the H5N1 strain, farm ministry officials said on Saturday, confirming the second such case in Japan this month.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="427">
<raw>
There have been no reported cases of human infection.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="428">
<raw>
Local officials were in the process of slaughtering all 50,000 birds on the farm after 3,200 of them died of the disease. Another 50,000 at an adjacent farm will also be slaughtered as a precautionary measure, a local official said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="429">
<raw>
Earlier tests had shown chickens on the farm in Miyazaki prefecture were infected with an H5 subtype of bird flu virus, but further testing had been needed to determine whether it was the H5N1 strain.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="430">
<raw>
The World Health Organization says the H5N1 virus has infected 269 people and killed 163 of them worldwide since 2003. Tens of millions of birds have been killed by the disease or culled to stop it spreading.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="431">
<raw>
Earlier this month, Japan suffered its first outbreak of H5N1 bird flu in poultry in more than three years, also in Miyazaki, which is the country's biggest poultry producing region.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="432">
<raw>
Cases of the disease have flared up across Asia in recent weeks, as in previous winters, killing six people this month in Indonesia and infecting poultry across parts of southern Vietnam.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="433">
<raw>
A 14-year-old boy in Azerbaijan was sent to hospital as a suspected case this week.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="434">
<raw>
The first outbreak of bird flu in the European Union this year was confirmed on Wednesday after the H5N1 strain was detected in geese in Hungary.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="435">
<raw>
UK gasses birds to halt deadly flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="436">
<raw>
POSTED: 11:00 p.m. EST, February 4, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="437">
<raw>
HOLTON, England (Reuters) -- Britain gassed tens of thousands of turkeys and extended restrictions on the movement of poultry on Sunday to try to prevent the spread of deadly bird flu from a farm in eastern England.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="438">
<raw>
The discovery of the highly pathogenic H5N1 strain of avian flu on a farm run by Europe's largest turkey producer surprised experts and raised questions about how the virus had been introduced into a sealed shed.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="439">
<raw>
However, the Department for the Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra) expressed optimism on Sunday that the virus had been confined to the Bernard Matthews farm near Lowestoft in the county of Suffolk.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="440">
<raw>
"Obviously, though, we need to be very vigilant in the coming days," a spokeswoman said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="441">
<raw>
The slaughter of 159,000 birds at the farm, which started late on Saturday, was expected to take another two days. The dead birds were being transported from the farm in sealed trucks to be incinerated.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="442">
<raw>
About 2,500 turkeys died in the initial outbreak of the virus, which appears to have been confined to one of 22 sheds at the farm.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="443">
<raw>
Restrictions on the movement of poultry were extended overnight to a 2,000-sq-km (775-sq-mile) area around the farm.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="444">
<raw>
Defra said the virus was the same pathogenic Asian strain found last month in Hungary where an outbreak among geese on a farm prompted the slaughter of thousands of birds.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="445">
<raw>
That outbreak followed a relative lull in cases of H5N1 among European poultry since hundreds of turkeys died at a farm in eastern France about a year ago.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="446">
<raw>
The strain tends to be transmitted to poultry by infected migrating wildfowl.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="447">
<raw>
It has killed at least 165 people worldwide since 2003, most of them in Asia, and more than 200 million birds have died from it, or been killed to prevent its spread.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="448">
<raw>
However. it has not yet fulfilled scientists' worst fears by mutating into a form that could be easily transmitted between humans and possibly cause a global pandemic.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="449">
<raw>
Thailand confirms 3rd case of H5N1
</raw>
</text>
<text id="450">
<raw>
POSTED: 10:58 p.m. EST, February 1, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="451">
<raw>
BANGKOK, Thailand (Reuters) -- The H5N1 bird-flu virus has re-appeared in a third Thai province, the country's third outbreak this year after a six-month lull, the Agriculture Ministry said on Friday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="452">
<raw>
All fowl in the immediate area around the outbreak in Ang Thong province, 105 km (65 miles) north of Bangkok were being slaughtered after 16 fighting cocks were confirmed to have died of bird flu, they said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="453">
<raw>
"The lab test has confirmed that the virus found in the province was the deadly H5N1," senior ministry official Pirom Srichan said on the Department of Livestock's Web site (www.dld.go.th).
</raw>
</text>
<text id="454">
<raw>
The virus reappeared in Thailand last month, in two provinces in the north and northeast.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="455">
<raw>
Thailand's previous outbreak of the virus in poultry was in July last year, and the last human death in August, the country's 17th since the virus re-emerged in Asia in late 2003.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="456">
<raw>
The World Health Organization says the virus has infected 267 people in 10 countries and killed 164 since 2003. There are fears that millions could die if the virus were to mutate into a form that passed easily from person to person.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="457">
<raw>
Jakarta cleans up backyard fowl
</raw>
</text>
<text id="458">
<raw>
POSTED: 9:45 p.m. EST, February 1, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="459">
<raw>
JAKARTA, Indonesia (AP) -- Indonesia claimed a major victory in the fight against bird flu Thursday, saying the heart of the capital had been cleared of backyard fowl and that residents elsewhere were handing in chickens for slaughter.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="460">
<raw>
But poultry could still be seen roaming freely in suburban neighborhoods, and some people hid pet birds in their homes, raising doubts the campaign would prevent further human deaths in the country hardest hit by the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="461">
<raw>
"I can guarantee there are no backyard birds in Central Jakarta," said Muhayat, the mayor, who uses a single name. "The people here are now fully aware of the disease and voluntarily culled their birds."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="462">
<raw>
Indonesia has tallied 63 human deaths from bird flu, nearly a third of the world's total. It came under criticism for failing to crack down on bird flu when it first appeared nearly four years ago, but has since taken concerted steps to stamp out the deadly H5N1 strain.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="463">
<raw>
Gov. Sutiyoso said he was pleased with progress so far in Jakarta, where owners have voluntarily slaughtered some 100,000 domestic chickens, racing pigeons and ducks in the last few weeks -- around a tenth of the estimated number in the capital.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="464">
<raw>
"People have to choose between the lives of their loved ones and the lives of their pets," he said, adding that authorities will show no tolerance for backyard birds or fowl in Jakarta.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="465">
<raw>
The H5N1 virus has killed or prompted the slaughter of millions of birds around the world since late 2003, and caused the deaths of at least 164 people worldwide, according to the World Health Organization.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="466">
<raw>
Most of the victims so far have been infected by contact with birds. But experts fear it could mutate into a form that easily spreads among humans, and start a pandemic with the potential to kill millions.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="467">
<raw>
In Lagos, Nigeria, meanwhile, shirtless young men slaughtered chickens with machetes, then poured their blood down an embankment as they talked about their nation's first bird-flu death, announced Tuesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="468">
<raw>
"Worried"
</raw>
</text>
<text id="469">
<raw>
"I'm worried about bird flu," said Philip Selli, a 32-year-old businessman in one of Lagos' main poultry markets, adding that he would only eat healthy ones. Experts say ingesting well-cooked chicken poses no health risk, but that close contact -- like plucking and cleaning sick birds -- can transmit the disease.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="470">
<raw>
Selli and others said the death of a 22-year-old university student on January 17 was unlikely to interrupt business in a city of 14 million, where most residents live in crowded slums, often together with poultry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="471">
<raw>
Indonesia, the world's fourth most populous country and home to hundreds of millions of backyard birds, is seen as a potential incubator for a bird flu capable of easy human-to-human transmission. The virus is already endemic in chickens across the nation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="472">
<raw>
Health Minister Siti Fadilah Supari said Indonesia has considered naming bird flu a national disaster -- a step that would mean money from the state budget's disaster fund could be spent on fighting it.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="473">
<raw>
The effectiveness of the slaughter campaign remained to be seen, amid fears that corrupt and underpaid officials may be susceptible to bribes or could simply stop enforcing the regulations.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="474">
<raw>
Lulu Anisa, 32-year-old housewife, said that while her chickens were seized by officials and culled on Thursday, "many residents managed to hide their birds."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="475">
<raw>
In Tokyo, meanwhile, officials confirmed that a bird-flu virus from the H5 family killed dozens of chickens in the fourth outbreak to hit Japan's poultry stocks this year.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="476">
<raw>
Authorities were still working to confirm if the outbreak of the virus in Shitomi, southwestern Miyazaki prefecture, was of the H5N1 strain deadly to humans, Agriculture Ministry official Yasushi Yamaguchi said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="477">
<raw>
Officials will slaughter the farm's 93,000 chickens and sterilize the site, the Ministry said in a statement.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="478">
<raw>
Chicken ranchers within a six-mile radius have already been told not to transport poultry out of the area.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="479">
<raw>
The bird-flu outbreak among poultry is the fourth this year in Japan and the third to hit farms in Miyazaki, Japan's largest chicken-producing region. All three previous outbreaks were confirmed as H5N1, and authorities have since culled thousands of birds to try to stop the spread of the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="480">
<raw>
Japan has confirmed only one human H5N1 infection, and no human deaths.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="481">
<raw>
Herpes outbreak triggers wrestling ban in Minnesota
</raw>
</text>
<text id="482">
<raw>
POSTED: 9:47 p.m. EST, January 31, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="483">
<raw>
CHICAGO, Illinois (Reuters) -- An outbreak of a contagious rash called herpes gladiatorum among Minnesota high school wrestlers led the state to suspend matches and halt contact practices, authorities said Wednesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="484">
<raw>
The eight-day suspension affecting 7,500 wrestlers on 262 teams was the first time a state's entire high school program in a sport has been shut down, authorities said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="485">
<raw>
The Minnesota State High School League acted after 24 wrestlers from 10 schools contracted the rash, which was first noticed and spread at a tournament in December.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="486">
<raw>
"I think it's a bold step by our high school league to protect our athletes -- and it's better now than at post-season tournament time," said Scot Davis, the wrestling coach at Owatonna Senior High School, whose wrestling program has one of the best records in the country.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="487">
<raw>
Davis said the suspension should allow infected wrestlers to recover as herpes usually disappears within 10 to 14 days. Any wrestler with the rash is barred from competing.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="488">
<raw>
Herpes gladiatorum -- commonly known as mat herpes because wrestlers are particularly susceptible -- is caused by contact with the same common herpes simplex virus that produces cold sores.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="489">
<raw>
A rash on the face or upper body is sometimes accompanied by itchiness, fever and sore throat, and it can cause blindness if it reaches the eyes. Some victims suffer recurring bouts throughout their lives.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="490">
<raw>
A spokeswoman for the American College of Sports Medicine said it was putting together a public education campaign about how to spot and contain outbreaks.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="491">
<raw>
Japan confirms third H5N1 outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="492">
<raw>
POSTED: 11:55 p.m. EST, January 30, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="493">
<raw>
TOKYO, Japan (AP) -- Dozens of chickens at a western Japan poultry farm died of the H5N1 bird flu strain, agriculture officials said Wednesday, fueling concerns about a series of recent cases in the country's poultry industry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="494">
<raw>
The bird flu outbreak in Okayama prefecture (state) was Japan's third this year involving the H5N1 strain.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="495">
<raw>
Two earlier outbreaks in southern Miyazaki prefecture (state) prompted the slaughter of thousands of chickens. Officials are still trying to determine whether another Miyazaki outbreak also involved H5N1.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="496">
<raw>
Authorities already began slaughtering chickens at the Okayama farm after the bird flu virus there was confirmed Tuesday to involve a virus from the H5 family, said ministry official Yasushi Yamaguchi.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="497">
<raw>
The farm has already been quarantined, and chicken ranchers within a 10-kilometer (six-mile) radius were told not to transport poultry or eggs out of the area.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="498">
<raw>
The H5N1 virus has prompted the slaughter of millions of birds across Asia since late 2003, and caused the deaths of at least 163 people worldwide, according to the World Health Organization.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="499">
<raw>
Japan has confirmed only one human H5N1 infection, and no human deaths.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="500">
<raw>
The bird-flu virus is hard for humans to catch, but international experts fear it could mutate into a form that could spread easily among people and possibly kill millions around the world.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="501">
<raw>
Norovirus sickens hundreds aboard QE2
</raw>
</text>
<text id="502">
<raw>
POSTED: 7:06 a.m. EST, January 25, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="503">
<raw>
SAN FRANCISCO, California (AP) -- A highly contagious form of stomach flu sickened hundreds of passengers during a worldwide voyage on the famed Queen Elizabeth 2 cruise ship in what health officials called an unusually large outbreak.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="504">
<raw>
The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention reported 276 passengers and 28 crew members had come down with norovirus by the time the ship docked Wednesday in San Francisco, California, for a regularly scheduled stop, though only four passengers remained sick.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="505">
<raw>
The CDC boarded the QE2 on Friday in Acapulco, Mexico, to investigate the outbreak.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="506">
<raw>
Investigators determined the emergency sanitation measures put in place by the ship's crew, from disinfecting casino chips to halting self-service at the ship's buffet, were containing the outbreak.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="507">
<raw>
"This one was a good example where they had a lot of cases but they did gain control over the spread of infection," Ames said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="508">
<raw>
The infections affected nearly 17 percent of the ship's 1,652 passengers, a particularly high percentage, said Jaret Ames, acting chief of the CDC's vessel sanitation program. By comparison, a norovirus outbreak last month aboard the world's largest cruise ship, Royal Caribbean's Freedom of the Seas, infected 338 passengers out of 3,823, or less than 9 percent.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="509">
<raw>
In rare cases, the elderly and young children can die from dehydration caused by norovirus symptoms. The infection, which ranks second only to the common cold in reported cases, usually clears up in two or three days with no lasting effects.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="510">
<raw>
No passengers have canceled their tickets as a result of the outbreak, said Brian O'Connor, a spokesman for Cunard Line, the company that operates the QE2.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="511">
<raw>
The ship departed January 8 from New York on the first leg of its 106-day cruise around the world. It was to leave San Francisco for Honolulu, Hawaii, on Wednesday night.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="512">
<raw>
H5N1 bird flu confirmed in Hungary
</raw>
</text>
<text id="513">
<raw>
BRUSSELS - An outbreak of the highly pathogenic H5NI strain of bird flu was confirmed in Hungary today, the European Commission said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="514">
<raw>
"The European Commission has been informed by the Hungarian authorities today of an outbreak of highly pathogenic avian influenza in Csongrad County, southeast Hungary," the EU executive said in a statement.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="515">
<raw>
Tests were carried out for bird flu after an abnormally high mortality rate was reported in a flock of over 3,000 geese. All of the remaining flock were culled, the Commission said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="516">
<raw>
Since 2003, outbreaks of bird flu have been confirmed in around 50 countries, killing more than 150 people according to World Health Organisation figures.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="517">
<raw>
LA hospital faulted for neonatal ICU bacteria outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="518">
<raw>
POSTED: 11:30 a.m. EST, January 24, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="519">
<raw>
LOS ANGELES, California (AP) -- Hospital staff did not properly clean medical instruments linked to a deadly bacterial outbreak at a neonatal intensive care unit, state regulators have concluded.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="520">
<raw>
White Memorial Medical Center closed the unit Dec. 4 after an outbreak of Pseudomonas aeruginosa sickened five infants. Two of the babies died, and their deaths were believed to have been caused by the pathogen.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="521">
<raw>
In a report issued Tuesday, inspectors from the California Department of Health Services faulted hospital staff for not following manufacturer's recommendations for sterilizing laryngoscope blades, which are used to insert breathing tubes. The report said the respiratory therapy staff simply wiped the blades with soap, tap water and alcohol wipes.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="522">
<raw>
A White Memorial statement said the report "confirms the hospital's preliminary findings."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="523">
<raw>
The neonatal unit has been reopened and officials said there have been no new infections.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="524">
<raw>
Of the roughly two million hospital-acquired infections each year, about 10 percent are caused by P. aeruginosa, a common bacterium that can be spread by health care workers, medical instruments, disinfectant solutions and food.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="525">
<raw>
Seoul: Powerful bird flu detected
</raw>
</text>
<text id="526">
<raw>
POSTED: 10:22 p.m. EST, January 19, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="527">
<raw>
SEOUL, South Korea (AP) -- South Korean quarantine officials are set to slaughter 386,000 poultry after an outbreak of a highly pathogenic version of bird flu, the agriculture ministry said Saturday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="528">
<raw>
The outbreak occurred at a chicken farm in Cheonan, about 92 kilometers (57 miles) south of Seoul, earlier this week, the fifth such outbreak since November, said Lee Joo-won, a ministry official.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="529">
<raw>
The official said it would take some time to confirm whether the virus is the deadly H5N1 strain of bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="530">
<raw>
South Korea culled 5.3 million birds during the last known outbreak of bird flu in 2003. The H5N1 virus began ravaging Asian poultry stocks in late 2003 and has killed more than 160 people worldwide.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="531">
<raw>
Most human cases have resulted from contact with infected birds. Scientists fear the virus could mutate into a form that is more easily transmitted between people, possibly creating a pandemic that could kill millions.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="532">
<raw>
Earlier this month, South Korean officials said that the deadly H5N1 strain of the virus had been transmitted to a human during a recent outbreak among poultry, but the person showed no symptoms of the disease as the poultry farm worker developed natural immunity to the disease.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="533">
<raw>
Hilton near Dulles closes after norovirus outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="534">
<raw>
POSTED: 1:09 p.m. EST, January 19, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="535">
<raw>
HERNDON, Virginia (AP) -- A Hilton hotel outside Washington has been closed for a top-to-bottom scrubbing after 15 employees and more than 100 guests were sickened by the highly contagious norovirus, a hotel spokesman said Friday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="536">
<raw>
Hotel officials first heard reports of sick guests Wednesday and contacted Fairfax County health authorities, said Jim Cree, the director of sales and marketing at the hotel near Dulles International Airport. Officials confirmed Thursday night that it was norovirus, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="537">
<raw>
"Yesterday we stopped taking reservations," Cree said. "Today we're actually relocating guests, and we've relocated all of our events to other hotels."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="538">
<raw>
Outbreaks of norovirus, which causes vomiting and diarrhea, are common on cruise ships and in places like hotels, prisons and nursing homes.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="539">
<raw>
Cree said the hotel would reopen Tuesday at noon.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="540">
<raw>
Bird flu reports spreading in Asia
</raw>
</text>
<text id="541">
<raw>
POSTED: 12:27 a.m. EST, January 16, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="542">
<raw>
JAKARTA, Indonesia (Reuters) -- An Indonesian hospital was on Monday overwhelmed with patients suffering bird flu symptoms while the virus spread further among flocks in Vietnam and flared anew in Thailand.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="543">
<raw>
A recent spurt of human infections with the H5N1 bird flu virus, which re-emerged in Asia in late 2003, has alarmed health officials.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="544">
<raw>
Four Indonesians have died this year after a six-week lull in cases, taking the number of people killed by bird flu in the country to 61, the highest in the world.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="545">
<raw>
At Jakarta's Persahabatan hospital, where doctors were treating 9 people with bird flu symptoms, including a 5-year-old girl in intensive care, its isolation wards were overwhelmed.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="546">
<raw>
"If we get more patients, we will send them to Sulianti Saroso," Muchtar Ichsan, the head of the bird flu ward, told Reuters, referring the country's main bird flu treatment centre in North Jakarta.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="547">
<raw>
The patients included the son and husband of a woman who died of bird flu last week. The 18-year-old son has been confirmed to have the disease, although tests so far on the husband show he does not have the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="548">
<raw>
In a bid to stem the spread of the virus, Indonesia plans to prohibit people from keeping backyard fowl in three high-risk provinces.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="549">
<raw>
Adding to regional worries, a senior Thai agriculture official said on Monday that 1,900 ducks had been culled in the northern province of Phitsanulok after some of the birds had tested positive for H5N1.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="550">
<raw>
The case is Thailand's first in birds since last July. The last human death -- the country's 17th -- occurred in August.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="551">
<raw>
Experts fear the H5N1 virus could mutate into a form that could spread easily between people, but there has been no evidence of human-to-human transmission of the virus so far in the latest cases.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="552">
<raw>
The World Health Organisation says bird flu has infected 267 people and killed 161 of them since 2003.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="553">
<raw>
Emergency levels
</raw>
</text>
<text id="554">
<raw>
The World Health Organisation (WHO) says the spike in cases in the northern hemisphere winter follows a similar pattern to that seen over the past three years and was to be expected.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="555">
<raw>
But it was encouraging that outbreaks were being quickly reported and dealt with, a senior WHO official said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="556">
<raw>
"It is not surprising that we are seeing an increase (in cases) ... but we are seeing much more effective responses than we were a few years ago," Keiji Fukuda, WHO's coordinator for the global influenza programme, told journalists.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="557">
<raw>
In Vietnam, where bird flu has killed 42 of the 93 people infected since 2003, the virus appeared to be spreading fast among fowl in the country's southern Mekong Delta, threatening to engulf the major rice-growing region.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="558">
<raw>
The Animal Health Department said in a report seen on Monday that tests showed H5N1 had killed ducks in the province of Soc Trang, just a day after bird flu was found in the neighbouring province of Tra Vinh.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="559">
<raw>
The Agriculture Ministry has ordered an additional poultry vaccination campaign in the Mekong Delta area and requested reinforcement of animal health teams to contain the spread.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="560">
<raw>
Farm ministry officials in Japan said there was no evidence of the disease spreading there following confirmation at the weekend of a bird flu outbreak at a poultry farm in the southwest in which 3,800 chickens died.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="561">
<raw>
Angolan cholera outbreak kills 2,760 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="562">
<raw>
POSTED: 10:25 a.m. EST, January 15, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="563">
<raw>
LUANDA, Angola (AP) -- More than 2,760 people have died of cholera in Angola since an epidemic broke out last February, authorities said Monday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="564">
<raw>
The Health Ministry said in a report it had recorded more than 69,000 cases of cholera and 2,764 fatalities.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="565">
<raw>
The epidemic, which started in Luanda, the capital, has spread to all but one of the southwest African country's 18 provinces.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="566">
<raw>
Foreign aid agencies have been distributing water dispensers, water purification tablets and soap in affected areas.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="567">
<raw>
Cholera is transmitted through contaminated water and is linked to poor hygiene, overcrowding and inadequate sanitation. Though it can be treated easily, cholera is a major killer in developing countries.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="568">
<raw>
Angola's health care and sanitation systems remain weak after a two-decade civil war that ended in 2002.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="569">
<raw>
Deaths as bird flu flares in Asia
</raw>
</text>
<text id="570">
<raw>
POSTED: 5:18 a.m. EST, January 10, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="571">
<raw>
BEIJING, China (Reuters) -- Bird flu has infected a farmer in China's first human case in months, killed an Indonesian teenager and spread deeper in Vietnam in a flare-up of infections mirroring past winters.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="572">
<raw>
A second Indonesian bird flu victim, a 37-year-old woman from Banten Province on Java island, was in hospital on Wednesday, the World Health Organization (WHO) said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="573">
<raw>
Most human victims of bird flu have contracted the virus from infected birds, usually chickens, ducks or geese and there is usually a surge in cases during cooler months when the virus seems to thrive.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="574">
<raw>
The 37-year-old Chinese man from the eastern province of Anhui kept backyard birds, but as in other human bird flu cases in China there was no reported poultry outbreak in the area, raising questions as to how he contracted the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="575">
<raw>
The man developed symptoms of fever and pneumonia early last month and was discharged from hospital on Saturday, the state-run Health News said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="576">
<raw>
"In China, the challenge is now to identify where this virus is hiding and how it is circulating," Henk Bekedam, the WHO's China representative, told Reuters.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="577">
<raw>
China has reported 22 human cases, including 14 deaths, since 2003 and, with the world's largest poultry population and millions of backyard birds roaming free, it is seen as a center in the fight against the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="578">
<raw>
Bekedam said that as vaccination rates for birds improve in China, detecting avian influenza becomes harder and harder, offering a possible explanation for why there was no reported outbreak where the farmer lived.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="579">
<raw>
Indonesia has the highest human death toll from bird flu of any nation, and on Wednesday that number grew to 58 when a boy, from Tangerang near Jakarta, died, said the head of the Indonesian health ministry's bird flu center Runizar Ruesin.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="580">
<raw>
The boy was admitted to hospital in the capital last week and deaths among poultry in his neighborhood had recently been reported, the WHO said in a statement posted on its Web site.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="581">
<raw>
Muhammad Nadirin, another official at the country's bird flu center, said hospital staff had to take extra care washing the boy's corpse because of concerns the virus might infect them.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="582">
<raw>
"He was washed using special protection methods to prevent contagion," but added he didn't know if it could be transmitted from human-to-human this way.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="583">
<raw>
The H5N1 virus mostly affects birds, but it has infected 263 people in 10 countries since 2003, killing 157 of them.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="584">
<raw>
Scientists fear the virus could mutate and spread rapidly between people, triggering a pandemic that could sweep the globe in weeks and possibly kill millions.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="585">
<raw>
An adviser to the White House said on Monday the number of people that could die in a flu pandemic that matches the 1918-19 outbreak will be "very scary" and far higher than the 62 million deaths forecast by a recent study by Harvard University.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="586">
<raw>
The 1918-19 "Spanish influenza" pandemic killed anywhere from 20 million to 100 million people.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="587">
<raw>
In Vietnam, bird flu has been confirmed in a fourth Vietnamese province after tests on 70 ducks showed they had died from the H5N1 virus, a government report said on Wednesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="588">
<raw>
The results of tests on ducks found dead at the weekend prompted health workers to slaughter around 1,800 more ducks in two communes of Kien Giang province in the southern Mekong Delta, the Animal Health Department report said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="589">
<raw>
The virus that first struck the delta region in late 2003 re-emerged last month. Vietnam has had no human H5N1 cases since November 2005.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="590">
<raw>
Officials: California lettuce possible Taco John's e. coli source
</raw>
</text>
<text id="591">
<raw>
POSTED: 1:50 p.m. EST, January 12, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="592">
<raw>
WASHINGTON (AP) -- Contaminated California-grown lettuce was the possible source of the E. coli outbreak that sickened more than 80 people late last year at Taco John's restaurants in two states, health officials said Friday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="593">
<raw>
State and federal investigators said they have matched the strain of the bacteria associated with the outbreak to two samples taken from dairy farms in California's Central Valley. The farms are located near lettuce fields, the Food and Drug Administration said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="594">
<raw>
Investigators continue to study whether bacteria-laden manure from the dairy farms could have contaminated the nearby lettuce-growing areas, the FDA said. The FDA said other sources of contamination were possible.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="595">
<raw>
The outbreak sickened about 81 people who had eaten at Taco John's restaurants in Minnesota and Iowa in November and December. Among those sickened, 26 were hospitalized. There were no deaths.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="596">
<raw>
The Taco John's outbreak occurred at roughly the same time as a separate and more widely publicized outbreak of food poisoning that sickened 70 patrons of Taco Bell restaurants in the Northeast. Though E. coli-contaminated iceberg lettuce was the likely culprit behind both outbreaks, the two are not thought to be linked.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="597">
<raw>
Friday's announcement also marks the second time in recent months that investigators have suggested Californian cattle or dairy operations as the source of contamination of produce grown on close-by fields. Bacteria tracked by wild pigs from a cattle ranch in California's Salinas Valley onto nearby spinach fields likely sparked an E. coli outbreak last year that sickened more than 200 people and killed three.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="598">
<raw>
Taco John's spokesman Brian Dixon said the Cheyenne, Wyoming, company had suspended purchases from the produce company that had supplied the three restaurants linked to the outbreak. The company also is in discussions with its other suppliers to do more testing of irrigation water and possibly to hold shipments of produce until samples can be tested for contamination, Dixon added.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="599">
<raw>
The recent spate of food-poisoning cases includes two salmonella outbreaks linked to fresh tomatoes that made about 400 people sick in October and November.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="600">
<raw>
The FDA said Friday it would step up its produce-safety efforts, including consideration of new regulations. The regulatory agency also plans to hold public meetings to discuss ways of improving the safety of fresh produce.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="601">
<raw>
And in Congress, Democrats in both the Senate and House plan to hold food-safety hearings in the coming months.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="602">
<raw>
China reports human bird flu case
</raw>
</text>
<text id="603">
<raw>
POSTED: 1:45 a.m. EST, January 10, 2007 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="604">
<raw>
BEIJING, China (Reuters) -- A Chinese farmer has contracted the H5N1 strain of bird flu, the country's first human case in months, leading to questions about whether the virus is circulating undetected among poultry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="605">
<raw>
The 37-year-old man surnamed Li from the eastern province of Anhui kept backyard birds, but as in other human bird flu cases in China there was no reported poultry outbreak in the area, raising questions as to how he contracted the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="606">
<raw>
"In China, the challenge is now to identify where this virus is hiding and how it is circulating," Henk Bekedam, the World Health Organisation's China representative, told Reuters.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="607">
<raw>
The country has reported a total of 22 human cases of bird flu, including 14 fatalities, since 2003, and with the world's largest poultry population and millions of backyard birds roaming free, it is seen as a center in the fight against the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="608">
<raw>
Bekedam said that as vaccination rates for birds improve in China, detecting avian influenza becomes harder and harder, offering a possible explanation for why there was no reported outbreak where Li lived.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="609">
<raw>
"It's not to say that the virus is not somehow still circulating, but that the detection of that circulating virus has become far much more difficult because of the active engagement of the government in avian influenza control," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="610">
<raw>
Li developed symptoms of fever and pneumonia on Dec. 10 and was discharged from hospital on Saturday in Tunxi in Anhui province after a full recovery, the Health News, the Health Ministry-run newspaper, said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="611">
<raw>
The Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention confirmed on Monday that he tested positive for the deadly H5N1 strain, which scientists fear could mutate into a form that can be passed easily between people, leading to a potential pandemic.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="612">
<raw>
People who have had close contact with Li were quarantined for medical observation until Dec. 29, the Health News said, but there was no indication that others in the area had taken ill.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="613">
<raw>
Bekedam said the WHO was still investigating whether any of Li's birds had been sick, adding it was possible that they carried H5N1 but did not display any symptoms.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="614">
<raw>
China has in the past been criticized for a lack of transparency in its handling of health threats, but Bekedam said the WHO was informed of Li's case as soon as he tested positive and praised the fact that he was tested a second time after his first tests turned up negative.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="615">
<raw>
"We think it's very encouraging that there seems to be some routine mechanisms in place to determine whether someone is suffering from avian influenza or not, and it doesn't stop after the first negative test," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="616">
<raw>
China last reported a human case of bird flu in July, when a farmer died of H5N1 in the northwestern region of Xinjiang. The most recent reported poultry outbreaks were in early October in the regions of Inner Mongolia and Ningxia.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="617">
<raw>
Norovirus cited in Olive Garden outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="618">
<raw>
POSTED: 1:48 p.m. EST, December 18, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="619">
<raw>
From Jennifer Pifer
</raw>
</text>
<text id="620">
<raw>
INDIANAPOLIS, Indiana (CNN) -- Health officials blamed a highly contagious, hard-to-get-rid-of virus for an outbreak of illness among nearly 400 patrons of an Olive Garden restaurant outside Indianapolis.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="621">
<raw>
Marion County Health Department spokesman John Althardt told CNN in a telephone interview that tests on three employees and one customer were positive for norovirus, which typically occurs in places such as cruise ships and restaurants where people are eating food prepared by others.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="622">
<raw>
Seventy-three cases were reported over the weekend, bringing the total to approximately 373, Althardt said. (Watch a victim describe his experience.  )
</raw>
</text>
<text id="623">
<raw>
The Olive Garden, which closed on Friday and scrubbed, has been given clearance to reopen.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="624">
<raw>
Marion County will monitor the restaurant to check on its compliance with health department recommendations.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="625">
<raw>
The sickened patrons reported symptoms including nausea, vomiting, diarrhea and, in some cases, fever. Three people remained hospitalized Monday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="626">
<raw>
Most Taco Bells reopen; senators call for investigation
</raw>
</text>
<text id="627">
<raw>
POSTED: 6:14 p.m. EST, December 12, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="628">
<raw>
DALLAS, Texas (CNN) -- Taco Bell reopened most of the more than 90 restaurants that it closed in the Northeast in recent weeks following an E. coli outbreak that sickened as many as 64 people, a company spokesman told CNN on Tuesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="629">
<raw>
Will Bortz said 30 restaurants -- four in New Jersey, two in Delaware and 24 in Pennsylvania -- remained closed. The New Jersey and Delaware restaurants should reopen Wednesday, he said. Taco Bell is working with the local health departments to reopen the Pennsylvania stores, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="630">
<raw>
But absent now from the 5,800 Taco Bells across the country are green onions, which were initially blamed for the outbreak. However, further testing on samples of green onions at the affected restaurants has not turned up any evidence of E. coli, and the search continues for the source of the infections.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="631">
<raw>
Four Democratic senators, meanwhile, called on federal agencies to launch a joint task force aimed at uncovering the real cause of the sickness. In a letter to the heads of the Food and Drug Administration, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the U.S. Department of Agriculture, the senators -- Hillary Clinton and Charles Schumer of New York, Dick Durbin of Illinois and Frank Lautenberg of New Jersey -- said the task force would "report to Congress and the public on the cause of these incidents and recommend changes in laws and regulations to protect American's food and health."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="632">
<raw>
Still seeking the source
</raw>
</text>
<text id="633">
<raw>
The CDC and state and local health officials are still interviewing those sickened to determine exactly what they ate and when to find the culprit.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="634">
<raw>
But company president Greg Creed reassured Taco Bell fans that all their food is safe.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="635">
<raw>
"We withdrew green onions from our restaurants but we also took the extra precaution to change our produce supplier in the Northeast," he told CNN's "American Morning."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="636">
<raw>
"We've taken all of those steps to ensure that the food is safe to eat at Taco Bell," Creed added.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="637">
<raw>
Workers also removed all food from the affected restaurants and re-sanitized everything, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="638">
<raw>
Creed said that to prevent such an outbreak from occurring again, his restaurant chain, owned by Yum Brands, would lead an industry-wide coalition to examine the safety of the produce food chain.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="639">
<raw>
"We've got to put in place even greater procedures to insure the safety of the food chain," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="640">
<raw>
Separately, white onions at a Taco Bell in Hempstead, New York, tested positive for E. coli Monday, said New York Health Department spokesman Marc Carey, but it was not the same strain as the E. coli involved in the outbreak.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="641">
<raw>
The white onion bag was open and the contamination could have happened on site, Carey said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="642">
<raw>
Meanwhile, a new outbreak of E. coli -- apparently connected to a different taco chain -- has shown up in Iowa.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="643">
<raw>
Kevin Teale of the Iowa Department of Health told CNN that approximately 40 people have reported symptoms consistent with E. coli, and 11 to 15 people have been hospitalized. The first illness was reported to the Black Hawk County Health Department on November 28, and the department has not seen any new cases since last week.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="644">
<raw>
The Associated Press has reported that those people became ill after eating at a Taco Johns restaurant in Cedar Falls.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="645">
<raw>
"As a precaution, all food that was being used in the restaurant was taken out of production and replaced with new food," said Taco John's president and CEO, Paul Fisherkeller.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="646">
<raw>
Escherichia coli bacteria are found in the intestinal tracts of humans and other animals. Most E. coli infections are associated with undercooked meat that has come in contact with animal feces.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="647">
<raw>
But the bacteria can also show up on leafy vegetables such as spinach and lettuce.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="648">
<raw>
Typically the bacteria are harmless, but certain strains can cause abdominal cramps, fever, kidney failure, bloody diarrhea, blindness, paralysis and even death.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="649">
<raw>
New bird flu case suspected at Japan poultry farm
</raw>
</text>
<text id="650">
<raw>
TOKYO - Japanese authorities are checking if bird flu killed more than 200 chickens at a poultry farm in southwestern Japan, the Agriculture Ministry said today.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="651">
<raw>
If confirmed, it would be the second outbreak this month of the H5N1 bird flu virus, which can be fatal to humans.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="652">
<raw>
The farm, which has about 50,000 birds, is situated in Hyuga in Miyazaki Prefecture, where 10 days ago the government confirmed an H5N1 outbreak -- Japan's first such case in three years.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="653">
<raw>
Miyazaki, on the southernmost main island of Kyushu, is the country's top breeder of chickens.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="654">
<raw>
In the latest suspected outbreak, 243 chickens had died on Monday, the Agricultural Ministry and Miyazaki government said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="655">
<raw>
Kyodo news agency said about 570 had died on Monday and Tuesday, but a Miyazaki official would not confirm that figure.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="656">
<raw>
A simple preliminary test for H5N1 showed positive for some birds, but more tests were needed for final confirmation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="657">
<raw>
In the earlier outbreak, the government imposed a 10-km (six-mile) quarantine zone around the infected farm, banning shipments of eggs and chickens to areas outside the zone.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="658">
<raw>
 Renewed fears over the disease have rippled across Asia in recent weeks. Hong Kong confirmed on Monday that three more dead birds found in the southern Chinese city carried the H5N1 virus, the third such case this month.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="659">
<raw>
Five people have died of bird flu in Indonesia since Jan. 1, while the virus has spread among poultry across parts of the Mekong Delta in Vietnam. Thailand reported its first outbreak in poultry in six months earlier this month.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="660">
<raw>
In 2004, Japan had four H5N1 poultry outbreaks between January and March, including one in Kyoto in western Japan that led to 240,000 chickens being culled and 20 million eggs destroyed.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="661">
<raw>
64 sickened by Taco Bell E. coli; more onions test positive
</raw>
</text>
<text id="662">
<raw>
POSTED: 2:15 a.m. EST, December 12, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="663">
<raw>
NEW YORK (CNN) -- Sixty-four cases of E. coli bacteria related to the outbreak that hit several Taco Bell restaurants in the Northeast in the past two weeks have now been confirmed, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="664">
<raw>
One of those cases includes the first confirmed case in New York City, CDC and New York state health officials say.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="665">
<raw>
Taco Bell officials said their restaurants are now completely safe for consumers.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="666">
<raw>
Although CDC officials said no food source has been confirmed in the outbreak, Taco Bell officials said the chain will no longer serve green onions, thought to be the most likely culprit in the spread of the bacteria.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="667">
<raw>
Meanwhile, white onions at a Taco Bell in Hempstead, New York, tested positive for E. coli Monday, said New York Health Department spokesman Marc Carey.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="668">
<raw>
But the strain was the same as the E. coli involved in the outbreak, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="669">
<raw>
The white onion bag was open and the contamination could have happened on site, Carey said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="670">
<raw>
"This was, as far as we can tell right now, an isolated incident, " he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="671">
<raw>
Escherichia coli bacteria is found in the intestinal tracts of humans and other animals. Most E. coli infections are associated with undercooked meat that has come in contact with animal feces.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="672">
<raw>
But the bacteria can also manifest itself on leafy vegetables such as spinach and lettuce.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="673">
<raw>
Typically the bacteria is harmless, but certain strains can cause abdominal cramps, fever, kidney failure, bloody diarrhea, blindness, paralysis and death. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="674">
<raw>
According to New York City Health Department spokesman Jeff Cowley, a Staten Island woman who became sick after eating at a Taco Bell was hospitalized November 24. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="675">
<raw>
But she wasn't tested for E. coli until the outbreak became widely publicized. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="676">
<raw>
Tests revealed she contracted the same strain of E. coli found in the other cases. The woman has since made a full recovery.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="677">
<raw>
New outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="678">
<raw>
A new outbreak of E. coli -- apparently connected to a different taco chain -- has shown up in Iowa.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="679">
<raw>
Kevin Teale of the Iowa Department of Health said approximately 40 people have reported symptoms consistent with E. coli and 14 people have been hospitalized. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="680">
<raw>
The first illness was reported to the Black Hawk County Health Department on November 28, and the department has not seen any new cases since last week.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="681">
<raw>
The Associated Press reported those people became ill after eating at a Taco John's restaurant in Cedar Falls.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="682">
<raw>
"As a precaution, all food that was being used in the restaurant was taken out of production and replaced with new food," said Taco John's president and CEO, Paul Fisherkeller.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="683">
<raw>
Test results on the suspected cases were expected to be completed Monday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="684">
<raw>
Taco Bell officials announced the chain will no longer serve green onions at any of its 5,800 restaurants nationwide.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="685">
<raw>
The ingredient was the only one to show positive results for E. coli in an independent test of more than 150 samples of all Taco Bell ingredients from several restaurants in multiple states, according to a Taco Bell statement.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="686">
<raw>
Taco Bell, which is owned by Yum Brands, has said it is confident it has taken all appropriate measures to ensure no more customers will become sick from its food. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="687">
<raw>
Officials said the company has closed, sanitized and restocked restaurants at several franchises and switched produce suppliers in the Northeast.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="688">
<raw>
E. coli outbreak now in 6 states; agencies focus on Taco Bell 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="689">
<raw>
POSTED: 12:00 p.m. EST, December 11, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="690">
<raw>
NEW YORK (CNN) -- More than 120 people in six states may be infected with the strain of E. coli bacteria involved in an outbreak that may be linked to Taco Bell restaurants, officials said Friday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="691">
<raw>
Sixty-three people have been confirmed to have the illness, the Food and Drug Administration said Friday afternoon, and state health agencies, earlier said about 60 other cases were under investigation. South Carolina and Utah are the latest states to report outbreaks.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="692">
<raw>
State and federal agencies are still trying to pin down the source, but the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention says the vast majority of the reported cases involved people who had eaten at Taco Bell restaurants before falling ill.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="693">
<raw>
Dr. Greg Braden of the CDC said his agency and state health departments have not seen any other sources of the illness and are zeroing in on Taco Bell and its suppliers.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="694">
<raw>
"We have some leads to say that it might be green onions, and that's based upon some preliminary testing that's been done in a number of laboratories right now," Braden said, "but the testing has not been confirmed, so we're keeping the options open, and the investigations that we're doing will be covering a wide range of foods, all of them served at Taco Bell specifically."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="695">
<raw>
On a voice recording for consumers looking for more information on E. coli, Taco Bell says, "Many of the people who reported becoming ill did not eat at Taco Bell."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="696">
<raw>
Representatives for the company could not provide an updated count of consumers who contracted E. coli after eating at its restaurants. Instead they referred CNN to the health departments of the states where cases have been identified or are suspected: New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Delaware, South Carolina and Utah.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="697">
<raw>
No case in Connecticut
</raw>
</text>
<text id="698">
<raw>
Earlier this week, state health officials in Connecticut suspected one case of E. coli, according to the FDA, but William Gerrish of the state's department of health told CNN Friday that there are no cases in the state.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="699">
<raw>
On Wednesday, Taco Bell said it had ordered the removal of all green onions from its 5,800 outlets nationwide, after three samples tested by an independent laboratory were found to be positive for E. coli.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="700">
<raw>
New Jersey health officials earlier this week focused attention on a food distribution warehouse in Burlington. Taco Bell would not confirm that the warehouse, operated by McLane Foodservice Inc., was being investigated.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="701">
<raw>
Ready Pac, a food distribution company that supplies Taco Bell's Northeast operations through a processing plant in Florence, New Jersey, says it stopped producing and shipping green onions to the restaurant's franchises on Wednesday after reports of the outbreak.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="702">
<raw>
The company released a statement saying it is working with regulatory agencies and industry experts to determine the source of the bacteria.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="703">
<raw>
Boskovich Farms in Oxnard, California, is a main provider of green onions to Taco Bell, but the company says it has not been contacted by the FDA or any government agencies although it is aware of the E. coli outbreak. The company said in a written statement that it is working closely with Taco Bell and Ready Pac to pinpoint the source of the bacteria.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="704">
<raw>
Two lawsuits relating to the outbreak have been filed against Taco Bell and its parent company, Yum Brands. The first was filed by the family of an 11-year-old New York boy, Tyler Vormittag. It claims the boy contracted E. coli after eating at a Taco Bell on November 24 in Riverhead.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="705">
<raw>
The second lawsuit was filed on behalf of Stephen Minnis of Montgomery County, Pennsylvania. Minnis, who was hospitalized twice because of symptoms related to the E. coli bacteria, is also filing suit against Boskovich Farms, according to his attorney, Drew Falkenstein.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="706">
<raw>
Northeast E. coli outbreak now in 5 states
</raw>
</text>
<text id="707">
<raw>
POSTED: 9:54 p.m. EST, December 7, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="708">
<raw>
NEW YORK (CNN) -- As many as 84 people in five Northeastern states have been confirmed as having the strain of E. coli bacteria involved in an outbreak believed to be linked to Taco Bell restaurants, officials said Thursday. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="709">
<raw>
State and federal agencies are still trying to pin down the source.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="710">
<raw>
At least one lawsuit relating to the outbreak already has been filed against the fast-food restaurant chain.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="711">
<raw>
E. coli cases -- first reported November 29 in New Jersey, followed by New York and Pennsylvania -- now have appeared in Delaware and Connecticut, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration said. Interviews showed that most of the first 58 people who became ill had eaten at Taco Bells.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="712">
<raw>
On Wednesday, Taco Bell said it had ordered the removal of all green onions from its 5,800 outlets nationwide, after three samples tested by an independent laboratory were found to be positive for E. coli.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="713">
<raw>
But now the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention is testing several ingredients used by Taco Bell. The epidemiology detectives are also conducting more interviews to track down the source of the E. coli strain, said Dave Daigle, spokesman for the Infectious Disease Center of the CDC.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="714">
<raw>
The Food and Drug Administration says at least 35 people have been hospitalized with the same E. coli strain since the outbreak, some in serious condition.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="715">
<raw>
The lawsuit was filed late Wednesday by the family of an 11-year-old Long Island boy, Tyler Vormittag, who they say contracted E. coli after eating at a Taco Bell on November 24 in Riverdale, New York.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="716">
<raw>
"When a restaurant serves food, there is the presumption that it is safe for human consumption," said the family's attorney, Andrew Siben. "Taco bell breached that duty when serving Mr. Vormittag a taco."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="717">
<raw>
He said the damages being sought will depend on the extent of injury to the fifth-grader. The suit was filed in New York State Supreme Court in Suffolk County.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="718">
<raw>
New Jersey health officials have focused attention on a food distribution warehouse in Burlington, New Jersey, and urged all Taco Bell locations that received shipments from there to "discard all current food supplies and clean and sanitize their facilities." Taco Bell would not confirm that the warehouse, operated by McLane Foodservice Inc., was being investigated.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="719">
<raw>
All but 30 Taco Bells reopened after E. coli outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="720">
<raw>
POSTED: 11:22 a.m. EST, December 13, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="721">
<raw>
DALLAS, Texas (CNN) -- Taco Bell reopened most of the more than 90 restaurants that it closed in the Northeast following an E. coli outbreak that sickened as many as 67 people, a company spokesman told CNN Tuesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="722">
<raw>
Will Bortz said 30 restaurants -- four in New Jersey, two in Delaware and 24 in Pennsylvania -- remained closed. The New Jersey and Delaware restaurants should reopen Wednesday, he said. Taco Bell is working with the local health departments to reopen the Pennsylvania stores, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="723">
<raw>
But absent now from the 5,800 Taco Bells across the country are green onions, which were initially blamed for the outbreak. However, further testing on samples of green onions at the affected restaurants has not turned up any evidence of E. coli, and the search goes on for the source of the infections. (Watch how the government is trying to improve food safety.  )
</raw>
</text>
<text id="724">
<raw>
Four Democratic senators, meanwhile, called on federal agencies to launch a joint task force aimed at uncovering the real cause of the sickness. In a letter to the heads of the Food and Drug Administration, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the U.S. Department of Agriculture, the senators -- Hillary Clinton and Charles Schumer of New York, Dick Durbin of Illinois and Frank Lautenberg of New Jersey -- said the task force would "report to Congress and the public on the cause of these incidents and recommend changes in laws and regulations to protect American's food and health."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="725">
<raw>
The CDC and state and local health officials are still interviewing those sickened to determine exactly what they ate and when to find the culprit.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="726">
<raw>
But company president Greg Creed reassured Taco Bell fans that all their food is safe.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="727">
<raw>
"We withdrew green onions from our restaurants but we also took the extra precaution to change our produce supplier in the Northeast," he told CNN's "American Morning."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="728">
<raw>
"We've taken all of those steps to ensure that the food is safe to eat at Taco Bell," Creed added.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="729">
<raw>
Workers also removed all food from the affected restaurants and re-sanitized everything, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="730">
<raw>
Creed said that to prevent such an outbreak from occurring again, his restaurant chain, owned by Yum Brands, would lead an industry-wide coalition to examine the safety of the produce food chain.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="731">
<raw>
"We've got to put in place even greater procedures to insure the safety of the food chain," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="732">
<raw>
Separately, white onions at a Taco Bell in Hempstead, New York, tested positive for E. coli on Monday, said New York Health Department spokesman Marc Carey, but it was not the same strain as the E. coli involved in the outbreak.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="733">
<raw>
The white onion bag was open and the contamination could have happened on site, Carey said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="734">
<raw>
Meanwhile, a new outbreak of E. coli -- apparently connected to a different taco chain -- has shown up in Iowa.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="735">
<raw>
Kevin Teale of the Iowa Department of Health told CNN that approximately 40 people have reported symptoms consistent with E. coli, and 11 to 15 people have been hospitalized. The first illness was reported to the Black Hawk County Health Department on Nov. 28, and the department has not seen any new cases since last week.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="736">
<raw>
The Associated Press has reported that those people became ill after eating at a Taco Johns restaurant in Cedar Falls.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="737">
<raw>
"As a precaution, all food that was being used in the restaurant was taken out of production and replaced with new food," said Taco John's president and CEO, Paul Fisherkeller.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="738">
<raw>
Escherichia coli bacteria are found in the intestinal tracts of humans and other animals. Most E. coli infections are associated with undercooked meat that has come in contact with animal feces.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="739">
<raw>
But the bacteria can also show up on leafy vegetables such as spinach and lettuce.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="740">
<raw>
Typically the bacteria are harmless, but certain strains can cause abdominal cramps, fever, kidney failure, bloody diarrhea, blindness, paralysis and even death.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="741">
<raw>
Saturday, October 21
</raw>
</text>
<text id="742">
<raw>
POSTED: 11:52 p.m. EDT, October 21, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="743">
<raw>
10 riverboat passengers hospitalized with flu-like symptoms
</raw>
</text>
<text id="744">
<raw>
(CNN) -- Ten riverboat passengers remained hospitalized in Henderson, Ky., late Saturday after complaining of flu-like symptoms while on a cruise.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="745">
<raw>
Tony Anglin, assistant director of nursing at Methodist Hospital, said 34 people were treated from the Mississippi Queen. None of the illnesses appear to be life-threatening, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="746">
<raw>
The cause of the outbreak, which is being called gastro-intestinal virus, is being investigated.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="747">
<raw>
The boat left Cincinnati, Ohio Wednesday on a cruise that was scheduled to arrive in St. Louis on Tuesday. It docked Friday night after more than two dozen of the ship's 525 passengers complained of feeling ill. (Posted 11:55 p.m.)
</raw>
</text>
<text id="748">
<raw>
3rd death linked to E. coli outbreak from tainted spinach
</raw>
</text>
<text id="749">
<raw>
POSTED: 9:47 p.m. EDT, October 6, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="750">
<raw>
(CNN) -- The death of an elderly Nebraska woman has been linked to an outbreak of E. coli from tainted spinach, state health officials said Friday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="751">
<raw>
Laboratory tests and DNA fingerprinting confirmed the death was from the O157:H7 strain of E. coli, the state Health and Human Services System said Friday. The woman died in late August, said spokeswoman Marla Augustine.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="752">
<raw>
Two other deaths -- a Wisconsin adult and a 2-year-old Idaho boy -- have also been determined to be from the E. coli outbreak.(Watch spinach going back in stores -- 1:53 )
</raw>
</text>
<text id="753">
<raw>
On Friday, the Food and Drug Administration said 199 people in 26 states had been sickened by the O157:H7 strain of E. coli.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="754">
<raw>
The state of Maryland has been investigating what federal officials have called a second "suspect case," an elderly woman who died Sept. 13 after consuming fresh spinach. Although E. coli was found in her body, DNA fingerprinting to confirm it was linked to the spinach has not been possible, the CDC said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="755">
<raw>
Federal officials have been investigating the outbreak, which was found to originate in spinach grown in three California counties. (Watch agents search produce plants -- 1:49 )
</raw>
</text>
<text id="756">
<raw>
Spinach fields combed in search for E. coli clues
</raw>
</text>
<text id="757">
<raw>
POSTED: 4:45 a.m. EDT, September 20, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="758">
<raw>
WASHINGTON (CNN) -- Investigators combed through farm fields in Monterey County, California, on Tuesday, searching for the source of an outbreak of illness linked to the consumption of raw spinach. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="759">
<raw>
A federal health official said Tuesday that the disease has affected 131 people in 21 states.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="760">
<raw>
That's up from 114 cases in 21 states on Monday, Dr. David Acheson, chief medical officer for the Food and Drug Administration's Center for Food Safety and Applied Nutrition, told reporters in a conference call.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="761">
<raw>
A 22nd state, Colorado, also reported a confirmed case, which the FDA had not yet added to its list. (Watch why the scare is widening -- 2:09)
</raw>
</text>
<text id="762">
<raw>
"There are no confirmed positives, but it's too early to have those yet," Acheson said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="763">
<raw>
Typically, about 25 percent to 30 percent of cases of E. coli infection require hospitalization. In the current outbreak, 66 of the 131 people infected by the 0157:H7 strain -- more than half -- have been hospitalized, and 20 of them have hemolytic uremic syndrome, a form of kidney failure, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="764">
<raw>
That could indicate the strain involved is particularly virulent, or it could mean simply that people with milder forms of the disease did not require medical attention and were not included in the case count, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="765">
<raw>
About three quarters of the cases in the outbreak are female, and two-thirds of the cases are among people ages 20-64.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="766">
<raw>
Acheson said three to four more days would elapse before the field tests would be able to confirm any positives on the nine farms initially tested, but he acknowledged that authorities may never find the source. (Watch as the CDC works to pinpoint the E. coli source -- 2:02)
</raw>
</text>
<text id="767">
<raw>
The farms all had contracted with Natural Selection Foods LLC, of San Juan Bautista, California, which last week issued a recall of its products containing spinach in brands packed with "Best if Used by Dates" of August 17, 2006 through October 1, 2006.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="768">
<raw>
A second recall, also announced last week, covered products containing spinach in brands sold by River Ranch, of Salinas, California. That company obtained its spinach from Natural Selection.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="769">
<raw>
The FDA has not changed its recommendation that consumers steer clear of any raw spinach until they have been able to pinpoint the source.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="770">
<raw>
The ban has hit hard in Monterey County, where nearly 125,000 tons of spinach were harvested from 10,451 acres of farmland in 2005.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="771">
<raw>
Acheson said he hoped, within 48 hours, to limit the search to a specific region in California "to see if we can get spinach not implicated back on the market in a safe way."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="772">
<raw>
"It's critical that we get our arms around this as fast as we can, and we're really trying to do that," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="773">
<raw>
The states involved in the outbreak and the number of cases are California (1), Connecticut (2), Idaho (5), Illinois (1), Indiana (8), Kentucky (6), Maine (2), Michigan (4), Minnesota (2), Nebraska (6), Nevada (5), New Mexico (2), New York (9), Ohio (15), Oregon (5), Pennsylvania (6), Utah (16), Virginia (1), Washington State (2), Wisconsin (32) and Wyoming (1).
</raw>
</text>
<text id="774">
<raw>
The first case occurred Aug. 2; onset of the most recent case occurred Sept. 9, Acheson said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="775">
<raw>
Symptoms of E. coli infection include diarrhea and vomiting, and the bacteria can lead to more severe complications, including anemia and kidney failure, particularly in the very young or elderly. Given that the maximum incubation period from time of exposure until symptoms is about a week, "you can figure that, by the end of this week, anybody who is going to get sick will have got sick," he said. (Watch why some fear the food supply is vulnerable -- 2:34)
</raw>
</text>
<text id="776">
<raw>
Federal health official have advised the public not to eat fresh spinach. No cases have been linked to frozen or canned spinach.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="777">
<raw>
Possible sources of contamination include water, agricultural practices, improper refrigeration, inadequate washing or any combination of those, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="778">
<raw>
E. coli spinach scare increases to 21 states
</raw>
</text>
<text id="779">
<raw>
POSTED: 6:08 a.m. EDT, September 19, 2006 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="780">
<raw>
WASHINGTON (CNN) -- The nationwide health scare over bacteria-ridden spinach widened Monday, as the number of states reporting sickness linked to the outbreak increased to 21.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="781">
<raw>
Illinois and Nebraska each reported a case linked to the E. coli bacteria alert believed to be caused by fresh spinach. Earlier Monday, the Food and Drug Administration widened its warning against eating any bagged spinach to include all fresh spinach. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="782">
<raw>
At least 111 people have become ill. One death is blamed on the outbreak.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="783">
<raw>
In the latest cases, an elderly woman in La Salle County, in northern Illinois, was hospitalized with kidney failure linked to E. coli thought to have been contracted from contaminated spinach, said Melaney Arnold, communications manager for the Illinois Department of Public Health.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="784">
<raw>
A Douglas County, Nebraska, resident was sickened by the same strain of the bacteria, the state's public health department said in a written statement. The patient did not require hospitalization and has since recovered.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="785">
<raw>
Dr. Robert Brackett of the FDA told CNN, "We've expanded the warning actually to all of the fresh spinach. That's because we learned that some of the companies that produced the consumer bag spinach also produced larger food-service size." (Watch why the scare is widening -- 2:09)
</raw>
</text>
<text id="786">
<raw>
Brackett said another concern is that restaurants or stores may use consumer-size bags of spinach to stock their salad bars or bulk bins.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="787">
<raw>
"We want to make sure consumers are aware that they don't consume any of the fresh spinach. We don't know whether it came from the bag or another state. We just don't have the focus down that much yet," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="788">
<raw>
Spinach producers are voluntarily recalling their products. Brackett said the FDA does not have the power to order a recall but is working with the producers.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="789">
<raw>
They do have the power to seize contaminated products, but Brackett said investigators can't do that until they determine the exact source of the contamination.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="790">
<raw>
"It could come from the irrigation water, animals in the field, from the workers, from a piece of equipment that's contaminated. We just don't know," he said. "Until we figure that out, we don't want to go down the wrong road. We're looking at all possibilities." (Watch how FDA searches for clues to outbreak -- 2:40)
</raw>
</text>
<text id="791">
<raw>
One death blamed on outbreak
</raw>
</text>
<text id="792">
<raw>
Investigators have blamed a death in Wisconsin on the outbreak, said Dr. David Acheson of the FDA.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="793">
<raw>
The victims are believed to be infected with the strain of E. coli called 0157:H7, he told reporters in a telephone conference call Sunday night. Fifty-six were hospitalized, at least 16 with a form of kidney failure called hemolytic uremic syndrome.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="794">
<raw>
As it is, he said, "This is unquestionably a significant outbreak."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="795">
<raw>
Also Sunday, authorities expanded their recall of products containing spinach to include "Spring Mix" made by the River Ranch Fresh Foods, LLC, in Salinas, California. The company obtained its spinach from Natural Selection, the company that issued the initial recall of spinach products on Friday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="796">
<raw>
Sunday's recall affects three brands: Farmers Market, Hy Vee and Fresh and Easy, Acheson said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="797">
<raw>
River Ranch President and CEO Robert V. Jenkins said he was advised Saturday of the need for the voluntary recall.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="798">
<raw>
"We are all eagerly waiting for them to come up with a cause for this so that we are able to identify solutions," he said. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="799">
<raw>
The ongoing investigation is being carried out jointly by the FDA and the California Department of Health Safety's Food and Drug Branch.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="800">
<raw>
Investigators will begin Monday carrying out "traceback" studies, where they go to the farms that grew the suspect vegetables for Natural Selection, to see if they can find the source of the bacteria.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="801">
<raw>
So far, the evidence implicating spinach is based on epidemiological data that show the people who became sick ate the spinach, Acheson said. It can take two weeks or longer from the time a person seeks medical attention until the time a laboratory is able to confirm the diagnosis, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="802">
<raw>
Asked if he had any advice for farmers, many of whom are bewildered over what they should do with the spinach in their fields, he said, "Given the state of the investigation, I don't."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="803">
<raw>
Asked when it would be safe for Americans to resume eating fresh spinach, he said, "As soon as we are sure that we've got this under control and that the outbreak is over and that we have figured out, as best we can, what the problems are and fixed them."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="804">
<raw>
No evidence of foul play
</raw>
</text>
<text id="805">
<raw>
Washing the leaves well will not necessarily offer protection, he said, noting that there is evidence that E. coli can get inside the leaf.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="806">
<raw>
The FDA said Friday it linked the outbreak to products packaged by the California-based Natural Selection Foods/Earthbound Farm. The company initiated a voluntary recall of all its spinach products with "best if used by" dates of August 17 through October 1.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="807">
<raw>
Asked whether terrorism or foul play may be involved, Acheson said he had seen no evidence to support that theory, but did not rule it out. "In my job, I always have to keep that in the back of my mind as a possibility," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="808">
<raw>
Acheson said the CDC determined that the first illness from E. coli bacteria happened August 2.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="809">
<raw>
Symptoms of E. coli infection include diarrhea and vomiting, and the bacteria can lead to more severe complications, particularly in the very young or elderly, including anemia and kidney failure.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="810">
<raw>
Indonesia now worst for bird flu
</raw>
</text>
<text id="811">
<raw>
Wednesday, August 9, 2006; Posted: 10:12 p.m. EDT (02:12 GMT) 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="812">
<raw>
JAKARTA, Indonesia (CNN) -- Two more people in Indonesia have died from avian influenza, the World Health Organization confirmed Thursday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="813">
<raw>
The deaths bring the total number of fatalities from bird flu in Indonesia to 44, the highest total for any single nation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="814">
<raw>
The latest victims were a 16-year-old boy from West Java Province and a 17-year-old girl from Jakarta Province.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="815">
<raw>
The male, Megi Saputra, who died on Monday from the lethal H5N1 strain of bird flu, had contact with sick and dying chickens in his household, the WHO said in a statement.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="816">
<raw>
Testing showed the H5 strain was present in the chickens. The boy's family members and close contacts were placed under surveillance.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="817">
<raw>
Earlier Tuesday, grieving relatives buried Megi at a family plot shaded by jackfruit trees close to his home in Bekasi. Meters away from the cemetery, villagers were rearing chickens in coops, The Associated Press reported.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="818">
<raw>
"I knew about bird flu from the TV and radio, but when my son got sick I had no clue it was bird flu," Megi's mother Sadiah said after the funeral. "I had no idea he was going to leave me."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="819">
<raw>
She told AP Megi was initially diagnosed with typhoid and told to go home.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="820">
<raw>
It was only four days after symptoms appeared that bird flu was suspected, and by then it was too late, Sadiah said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="821">
<raw>
The teenage girl died on Tuesday. An investigation found that pet pigeons were kept inside her home and that several homes in the area had flocks of backyard poultry, the WHO said. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="822">
<raw>
"Animal health authorities have collected samples from birds in the neighborhood and these will be tested as part of the continuing investigation."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="823">
<raw>
To date, 56 human cases of bird flu have been confirmed in Indonesia. Of those, 44 have been fatal.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="824">
<raw>
Vietnam is the second worst hit at 42, but it has not recorded any deaths in 2006.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="825">
<raw>
Experts say Indonesians will continue to die until the nation stops the rampant spread of infection among its hundreds of millions of backyard poultry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="826">
<raw>
"You've got to worry about the humans, but if you don't clean up the animals, it doesn't matter what you do," Dr. Anthony Fauci, the U.S. National Institutes of Health's infectious disease chief told The Associated Press by phone.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="827">
<raw>
Vietnam largely controlled the spread of the virus by launching a nationwide mass vaccination campaign in poultry last year, AP reports.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="828">
<raw>
Thailand, which has reported 16 deaths, relies on strong village-based surveillance and mass slaughtering when outbreaks are discovered.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="829">
<raw>
Overall, 236 human cases of bird flu have been identified in 10 countries -- Azerbaijan, Cambodia, China, Djibouti, Egypt, Indonesia, Iraq, Thailand, Turkey and Vietnam -- as of Thursday, the WHO said. Of those, 138 cases have been fatal.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="830">
<raw>
Canada confirms seventh case of mad cow disease
</raw>
</text>
<text id="831">
<raw>
Thursday, July 13, 2006; Posted: 4:41 p.m. EDT (20:41 GMT) 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="832">
<raw>
(CNN) -- Canadian health officials said Thursday that tests have confirmed a seventh case of mad cow disease, in a 50-month-old dairy cow from Alberta.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="833">
<raw>
"The entire carcass has been incinerated and did not enter the human or animal feed systems," the Canadian Food Inspection Agency said in a posting on its Web site.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="834">
<raw>
The agency said it has located the birth farm, and investigators are tracing other cattle born there within a year of the affected animal's birth.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="835">
<raw>
The animal's age means it contracted the disease -- also known as bovine spongiform encephalopathy -- after the 1997 feed ban intended to halt such cases.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="836">
<raw>
CFIA said it will investigate how it might have been exposed and has invited U.S. officials to participate in the effort.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="837">
<raw>
"While the United States and Canada have a strong system in place to protect animal and human health, the diagnosis of BSE in an animal born roughly four and half years after the implementation of the 1997 ruminant-to-ruminant feed ban does raise questions that must be answered," Agriculture Secretary Mike Johanns said in a written statement.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="838">
<raw>
"We need a thorough understanding of all the circumstances involved in this case to assure our consumers that Canada's regulatory system is effectively providing the utmost protections to consumers and livestock."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="839">
<raw>
The animal's age "does raise questions," the spokesman said. "We would like to have answers."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="840">
<raw>
The Canadian government last month tightened its regulations on animal feed, and sought Monday -- when preliminary tests indicated the cow was a suspect case -- to downplay the risk.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="841">
<raw>
"The safety of Canada's food supply remains protected through the removal of specified risk material (SRM) from all cattle slaughtered for human consumption," it said. "SRM are cattle tissues that have been shown in infected cattle to contain concentrated levels of the BSE agent. This measure is internationally recognized as the most effective means to protect the safety of food from BSE."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="842">
<raw>
But Caroline Smith DeWaal, food safety director for the Center for Science in the Public Interest, called the report "troubling."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="843">
<raw>
"This is a very young cow to be infected with BSE," she said in a telephone interview. "The animal would have been born five years after this feed ban was implemented, so I think this is a troubling new finding, and one that would certainly indicate the failure of the feed ban in Canada."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="844">
<raw>
Most other animals that contracted the disease were born before or around the time of the national ban, she said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="845">
<raw>
In April, the Canadian government confirmed a case of mad-cow disease in a cow in British Columbia.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="846">
<raw>
The country's surveillance program has now detected seven BSE-infected animals since it was put in place in 2003.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="847">
<raw>
In March, Alabama officials announced the third case of mad-cow in the United States.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="848">
<raw>
Eating infected tissue from cows has been linked to a variant of Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, a rare but fatal degenerative disease blamed for the deaths of 150 people.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="849">
<raw>
Indonesia reports two more human bird flu cases
</raw>
</text>
<text id="850">
<raw>
JAKARTA - Indonesia has confirmed two new human cases of bird flu, with both victims alive and being treated in a Jakarta hospital, a health ministry official said on Monday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="851">
<raw>
Confirmation came from two tests, Dr Muhammad Nadhirin, from the ministry's national bird flu centre, told Reuters.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="852">
<raw>
"The position is 74 cases, 55 of whom have died," he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="853">
<raw>
One of the victims of the virus is a 35-year-old woman and the other a 2-1/2-year-old boy. The two are not related and are from different parts of West Java province.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="854">
<raw>
Nadhirin said it had not yet been determined whether the two had contact with fowl, the most common way for humans to catch bird flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="855">
<raw>
Bird flu remains essentially an animal disease but it has infected more than 250 people worldwide since late 2003, killing more than 150, according to the World Health Organisation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="856">
<raw>
Indonesia has become one of the frontlines in the battle against the disease. No country has suffered from more deaths than this huge Asian country of 17,000 islands where millions of chickens roam backyards freely.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="857">
<raw>
 Despite the rise in the human death toll, the Indonesian government has resisted mass culling of birds, citing the expense and impracticality in a sprawling, populous country where many people are still unperturbed by the bird flu threat.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="858">
<raw>
The number of provinces where bird flu is endemic has nearly halved in the last six months, although all areas on heavily populated Java island remain affected, officials say.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="859">
<raw>
Scientists fear the virus could mutate into a form that can be passed easily between people, leading to a possible human pandemic which could kill millions.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="860">
<raw>
6 more bird flu cases in Indonesia
</raw>
</text>
<text id="861">
<raw>
Monday, May 29, 2006; Posted: 6:17 p.m. EDT (22:17 GMT) 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="862">
<raw>
(CNN) -- Six more human cases of the H5N1 strain of avian flu have occurred in Indonesia, the World Health Organization has said, citing Indonesia's Ministry of Health.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="863">
<raw>
Three of the cases were fatal.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="864">
<raw>
That means 48 of the 224 human cases confirmed worldwide by the organization have occurred in Indonesia. Thirty-six of the Indonesian cases have proven fatal.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="865">
<raw>
Only Vietnam, with 93 cases, 42 of them fatal, has tallied more.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="866">
<raw>
Four of the infected people had been exposed to chickens or pigeon feces. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="867">
<raw>
Investigators are still looking into how the other two contracted the virus.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="868">
<raw>
WHO spokesman Dick Thompson told CNN it was highly unlikely that human-to-human transmission was responsible for any of the six cases, given that all but two they were separated by great distances.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="869">
<raw>
And those two -- a brother and sister who have since died -- both got sick on the same day, making it unlikely one could have infected the other, Thompson said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="870">
<raw>
The six new cases are not related to a cluster of at least seven cases -- all of them blood relatives -- reported last week in Kubu Sembelang village, Karo District, of North Sumatra, Thompson said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="871">
<raw>
WHO has said the virus in that cluster may have been spread by human-to-human contact. The overwhelming majority of human cases to date have been linked to exposure to poultry.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="872">
<raw>
Seven of eight family members died in the outbreak. The first case was not confirmed to be H5N1 since the body was buried without tissue samples being taken.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="873">
<raw>
Health officials have long been concerned that a mutation in the virus would make it spread easily among humans. But laboratory tests show that has not happened, Thompson said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="874">
<raw>
Researchers are working on the hypothesis that the family members involved in the cluster were genetically more susceptible to H5N1, since spouses did not get sick, Thompson said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="875">
<raw>
Mad-cow disease confirmed in Canada
</raw>
</text>
<text id="876">
<raw>
Government: Finding does not affect safety of nation's beef
</raw>
</text>
<text id="877">
<raw>
Monday, April 17, 2006; Posted: 3:03 a.m. EDT (07:03 GMT) 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="878">
<raw>
(CNN) -- The Canadian government said Sunday that it has confirmed a case of mad-cow disease in a cow in British Columbia.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="879">
<raw>
The dairy cow did not enter human or animal feed chains, the Canadian Food Inspection Agency said in a written statement.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="880">
<raw>
The 6-year-old dairy cow was identified on a Fraser Valley farm through a national surveillance program for mad-cow disease.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="881">
<raw>
Mad-cow disease is also known as bovine spongiform encephalopathy (BSE), a degenerative disease of the central nervous system of cattle. There is no cure and no test to determine whether it exists in live animals or in muscle tissue, according to the U.S. Department of Agriculture.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="882">
<raw>
"This finding does not affect the safety of Canadian beef," the agency said Sunday in a written statement. "Tissues in which BSE is known to concentrate in infected animals are removed from all cattle slaughtered in Canada for domestic and international human consumption."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="883">
<raw>
Investigators have identified the animal's date and location of birth in order to trace potential sources of infection, which include feed the animal may have eaten early in its life, when cattle are most susceptible to the disease.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="884">
<raw>
Though regulations were enacted during the 1990s banning the feeding to cows of ruminant material that could be contaminated with BSE, "an enhanced feed ban would accelerate the eradication of BSE in Canada," the government said Sunday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="885">
<raw>
"Accordingly, the CFIA has published proposed regulatory amendments, and following extensive consultations, is now in the process of finalizing their content."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="886">
<raw>
The national surveillance program has detected five BSE-infected animals since it was put in place in 2003. The program targets cattle most at risk, and since its inception has tested more than 100,000 animals. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="887">
<raw>
Last month, Alabama officials announced the third case of mad-cow disease in the United States.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="888">
<raw>
U.S. Agriculture Secretary Mike Johanns said he would dispatch a USDA animal health expert to Canada Monday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="889">
<raw>
"Information gathered through this investigation will help us to determine what, if any, impact this should have on our beef and live cattle trade with Canada," he said. "Based on the information currently available, I do not anticipate a change in the status of our trade."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="890">
<raw>
Canada's trade with the United States in cows younger than 30 months, as well as meat, resumed in July 2005 because the younger cows are thought to have a lower disease risk, The Associated Press reported.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="891">
<raw>
In humans, eating infected tissue from cows has been linked to a variant of Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, a rare but fatal degenerative disease blamed for the deaths of 150 people in Britain, where there was an outbreak in the 1980s and 1990s.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="892">
<raw>
Mumps outbreak now in 8 states
</raw>
</text>
<text id="893">
<raw>
CDC tracks airline passengers for possible exposure 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="894">
<raw>
Friday, April 14, 2006; Posted: 10:55 p.m. EDT (02:55 GMT) 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="895">
<raw>
CNN) -- Federal health officials said Friday they are looking into whether air travel is spreading mumps through the Midwest.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="896">
<raw>
Iowa has seen an epidemic of more than 600 suspected cases since December, according to a Centers for Disease Control and Prevention spokesman. Other states reporting cases are Illinois, Kansas, Minnesota, Missouri, Nebraska and Wisconsin. The agency has not yet released the name of the eighth Midwestern state.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="897">
<raw>
Most of the Iowa mumps cases are on college campuses, where the typical close living quarters make an ideal breeding ground for the virus. (Watch as officials try to figure out how many people may have been exposed -- 1:45) 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="898">
<raw>
The CDC has initiated a multistate investigation, involving state health departments, to notify passengers who were potentially exposed to two mumps-infected travelers who took nine flights on two air carriers. The agency has also been using a new computer program to track air travelers who may be virus carriers. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="899">
<raw>
The CDC has identified five Northwest Airlines flights taken on March 26-29 that had stops in Iowa, Minnesota, Michigan and Washington; and four American Airlines flights taken on April 2 with stops in Arizona, Texas, Arkansas, Missouri and Iowa. (More on one passenger)
</raw>
</text>
<text id="900">
<raw>
So far, no cases involving mumps transmission on those flights have been reported, CDC spokesman Curtis Allen said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="901">
<raw>
"We suspect the transmission would be very low on airline flights, ... but probably not zero," Allen added.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="902">
<raw>
The mumps outbreak is the nation's largest in 20 years, according to Allen. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="903">
<raw>
"We suspect it was importation from another country. There was an ongoing outbreak in Great Britain recently," Allen said. "But we can't confirm that was the source."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="904">
<raw>
Still, he added, "Many of these diseases [mumps and others] are just a plane ride away."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="905">
<raw>
Mumps is caused by a virus and spread by coughing and sneezing, but it is not "as contagious as influenza or measles," Allen said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="906">
<raw>
Doctors say that dealing with the mumps outbreak provides a testing opportunity for outbreaks of other diseases, such as bird flu. It also tests a system put into place after the September 11, 2001, terrorist attacks to deal more effectively with biological emergencies.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="907">
<raw>
"We can take this mumps epidemic as kind of a fire drill for what might happen if bird flu suddenly became transmissible to humans and was introduced into the United States," said Dr. William Schaffner of the Vanderbilt University Medical Center.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="908">
<raw>
Mumps is contagious from three days before a person feels ill until nine days after the onset of symptoms, according to the CDC. There is no treatment for the disease, the CDC says on its Web site; the disease must run its course.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="909">
<raw>
The best protection against mumps, Allen said, is to be vaccinated. One dose is about 80 percent effective, and two doses, which is what most U.S. children get, work about 95 percent of the time, Allen said. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="910">
<raw>
The introduction of the vaccine in 1967 has helped reduce mumps cases in the United States by 99 percent, he said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="911">
<raw>
Before use of the vaccine became common, almost everyone in the United States contracted mumps, and 90 percent of cases occurred among children younger than 15, according to a CDC report. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="912">
<raw>
The CDC report said that in 1977 Iowa law required a single dose of a combined measles, mumps and rubella vaccine for entry to public schools; in 1991 the requirement rose to two doses; and in 2004-05 97 percent of Iowa schoolchildren received two doses of MMR vaccine. 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="913">
<raw>
Indonesia bird flu death confirmed
</raw>
</text>
<text id="914">
<raw>
Burkina Faso reports bird flu among guinea fowl 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="915">
<raw>
Tuesday, April 4, 2006; Posted: 12:05 p.m. EDT (16:05 GMT) 
</raw>
</text>
<text id="916">
<raw>
(CNN) -- A young girl in Indonesia died of highly pathogenic bird flu last month, bringing the country's total number of confirmed H5N1 human cases to 30, the World Health Organization announced Tuesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="917">
<raw>
Of those cases, 23 have been fatal, including the 20-month-old. She developed a fever and cough on March 17, was hospitalized March 22 and died the next day, the WHO said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="918">
<raw>
Several chickens near her home in Kapuk, West Jakarta, died from the highly pathogenic form of bird flu about a week before she started to develop symptoms.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="919">
<raw>
The girl's relatives and neighbors are being tested for bird flu, and preliminary results are negative, although they are still under observation.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="920">
<raw>
The H5N1 virus has infected humans in nine countries across Asia and Africa. The WHO has confirmed 191 human cases worldwide; of those, 108 died.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="921">
<raw>
The virus has spread to birds in the small West African nation of Burkina Faso, the World Organization for Animal Health (OIE) confirmed Tuesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="922">
<raw>
The outbreak began on March 1 at a camp site in Gampela, about 10 miles east of the capital Ouagadougou, among some 123 helmeted guinea fowl who died, the OIE reported.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="923">
<raw>
Guinea fowl -- ground-dwelling, pheasant-like birds native to sub-Saharan Africa -- are often domesticated and eaten by humans.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="924">
<raw>
Local authorities have quarantined the area and plan to vaccinate or cull poultry on nearby farms.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="925">
<raw>
Bird-flu laws must be clear and set out early, says Palmer
</raw>
</text>
<text id="926">
<raw>
Officials will be able to assume draconian laws if bird flu hits here, the Law Commission says. Picture/Reuters
</raw>
</text>
<text id="927">
<raw>
Parliament should set out what laws and regulations will be suspended or enforced during a bird flu pandemic before the disease hits, the Law Commission says.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="928">
<raw>
The Epidemic Preparedness Bill, being considered by the Government administration select committee, allows ministers to relax statutory restrictions or requirements to deal with the flu.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="929">
<raw>
However, Law Commissioner Sir Geoffrey Palmer told it yesterday the term "relaxation" seemed to be new and, while it appeared to amount to a suspension of the law, it lacked clear definition.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="930">
<raw>
"The power is wide and the way it will be used is difficult to predict."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="931">
<raw>
While acknowledging that it would be virtually impossible to identify every statute which might need to be modified if a pandemic struck the country, Sir Geoffrey said it would be simpler and more transparent to set out some regulations before the event.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="932">
<raw>
"The actions that need to be taken should be clear to the health authorities from their operational plan for such events. The bulk of what is required should be capable of being dealt with in advance of the epidemic if planning for it is well advanced," the commission's submission said.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="933">
<raw>
 Sir Geoffrey said a pandemic would see politicians and officials able to assume draconian powers over people's individual rights. Those rights could not be suspended without real justification, so those powers should be scrutinised by Parliament before the event so that everyone knew what they were and officials knew what was expected of them.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="934">
<raw>
Regulations being set out in advance of any pandemic would also help after the event, during any review of whether officials had exceeded their powers or not.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="935">
<raw>
"It is better in our view to make as many plans in advance as can usefully be made. The powers that are needed should be defined and drafted, the regulations scrutinised and only those matters that have not been properly anticipated dealt with by emergency regulations."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="936">
<raw>
Hospitalised Indonesian woman has bird flu, official says
</raw>
</text>
<text id="937">
<raw>
JAKARTA - An Indonesian woman being treated in hospital has tested positive for bird flu, a health official said on Wednesday.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="938">
<raw>
Indonesia has become one of the frontlines in the battle against the disease. So far, 52 people have died of bird flu, the highest of any country, with the majority of deaths occurring since the beginning of this year.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="939">
<raw>
"A 67-year-old woman living in the Cisarua area of Bandung had contact with fowl," the official from the bird flu information centre said by telephone. The woman was admitted to the hospital on October 7 and was still alive, the official added.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="940">
<raw>
The woman tested positive to the H5N1 virus after a test at a health ministry laboratory and one conducted by NAMRU, the US Naval Medical Research Unit based in Jakarta, the official added.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="941">
<raw>
Hadi Yusuf, the director of the Hasan Sadikin hospital in Bandung, southeast of the capital Jakarta, said the woman was being treated with the anti-viral drug Tamiflu and antibiotics.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="942">
<raw>
"Her condition is bad. For a second day, she has been on a respirator and her blood pressure is high."
</raw>
</text>
<text id="943">
<raw>
 Yusuf said the woman had come down with a fever two weeks after being in the vicinity of dead chickens.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="944">
<raw>
Despite the rise in the human death toll, the Indonesian government has resisted mass culling of birds, citing the expense and impracticality in a huge, populous country where keeping a few chickens or ducks in backyards is common.
</raw>
</text>
<text id="945">
<raw>
Worldwide, 148 people have died of bird flu since 2003.
</raw>
</text>
